aboard.
aboard.
Welcome to the Institute of Science and Technology of the Central Institute of Science and Technology.
Welcome to the Institute of Science and Technology of the Central Institute of Science and Technology.
I am the director of the Institute of Science and Technology of the Central Institute of Science and Technology.
I am the director of the Institute of Science and Technology of the Central Institute of Science and Technology.
I am honored to be able to introduce today's host.
I am honored to be able to introduce today's host.
Vice President Wang Jingxing of our Central Plains Institute
我們中原院的王靖星副院長
here?
在座呢
because our guest
因為我們的貴賓
He is our new Secretary-General of the Central Plains Academy
就是我們新任的中原院秘書長
Secretary Peng Jinkun Peng
彭金坤彭秘書長
OK, then I'll hand the mic over to today's host.
好 那我就把麥克風交給今天的主持人
this
這個
thanks for this our host
謝謝這個我們的主人
Director Chen
這個陳所長
Thank you all so much for taking the time out of your busy schedule to listen to this
那也非常感謝各位百忙之中來聽這個
Share this Feast of Wisdom
分享這個智慧的饗宴
That
那
Logically, I just want to introduce
照道理我就是要介紹
this our keynote speaker
這個我們的主講者
what about the fact
那事實上呢
our keynote speaker
我們的主講者
For the people of National Taiwan University
對臺大的人來講
no stranger
並不陌生
In fact, he has been
其實他長期在
Our National Taiwan University
我們臺灣大學
Serve hard
把力氣服務
Poached by Central Researcher
被中央研究員挖腳
is now the director of our Central Fellows Institute of Law
現在是我們這個中央研究員法律研究所的所長
he was also a justice
他也當過大法官
So everyone is familiar with his name
所以在大家對他的名字也不陌生
Sometimes I have seen his name in the media magazines before
有時候以前在媒體爆章雜誌都看過他的大名
listened to his advice
聆聽過他的高見
then i am
那我就是
Actually, he's an old friend to me personally.
其實他對我個人來講是老朋友
Because he went to Harvard University in the United States for a year
因為他有一年到美國的哈佛大學去
this for research
這個做研究
we just met there
我們那時候剛好在那兒碰到
Then I still wish to compare some of his
那我還是心裡如意把他的一些比較
objective study
客觀的求學的
After sharing this report with everyone
經過跟大家這個報告
Of course he didn't have to say he was
他當然不用講他是
Graduated from the Law Department of National Taiwan University
臺灣大學法律系畢業
That also went to graduate school
那也讀了研究所
Then he later in the United States
那他後來在美國
Connors University
Connors University
Cornell University's Juris Doctor
康乃爾大學的法學博士
that he
那他
It is now our Academia Sinica's Institute of Law
現在是我們的中央研究院的法律研究所的
Distinguished Researcher and Director
特聘研究員兼所長
So a Distinguished Researcher is equivalent to a University Chair Professor
所以特聘研究員就是等於是大學的講座教授
But he is also from the law school of our National Taiwan University.
那但是他也是我們臺灣大學的法學院的
part-time professor
兼任教授
his long-standing commitment to the constitution
他長期致力憲法
Freedom of Speech Privacy
言論自由 隱私權
Research in the Field of Information Law
資訊法領域的研究
Then this is like what I just said
那這個就像我剛在所講
He stayed in Taiwan University for a long time
他在臺大待過很長的一段時間
He was from 1978 to 2003
他從1978年到2003年
He served as a teaching assistant in the law department of National Taiwan University
他在臺灣大學擔任過法律系的助教
Lecturer Associate Professor Professor
講師 副教授 教授
2003 to 2011
2003年到2011年
chief justice of the judiciary
擔任司法院的大法官
Well, this is generally what legal people envy the most in the future is to become a university student.
那這一般是法律人最羨慕將來就是當大
The judge did this, and he did it.
法官這樣 他也都做到了
Then he will talk about one today
那他今天要講一個是一個
very important topic
非常重要的題目
There are some special revelations for our reality
對我們現實特別有一些啟示
privacy in the information society
就是資訊社會中的隱私
privacy
隱私權
i remember i was in the 1980s
我記得我在1980年代
While studying at Harvard
在哈佛讀書的時候
There is a very famous professor at Harvard University
哈佛大學有一個很出名的教授
Called Daniel Bale
叫Daniel Bale
He learns a famous book
他學一個名著
就是The Coming of the Poster Industrial Society
就是The Coming of the Poster Industrial Society
With the advent of the post-industrial society
就後工業社會的來臨這樣
Then think about thirty years ago
那這想三十幾年前
That computer is definitely something only the rich can afford.
那電腦絕對是只有有錢能買得起
They're all big, big computers.
都是很大很大的電腦
But then you have to think about saying
但那時候都要想到說
invention of computer
電腦的發明
will change the future of mankind
將會改變人類未來的
Organization Structure Even Behavior
組織 結構 甚至行為
But from thirty years later you see
但從三十幾年後你看
Sure enough, you see that this has changed so much
果然是你看這個變化這麼多
like us now
現在像我們
It's hard for someone like me to understand
我這種人都很難了解說
This world has become very strange to me
這個世界對我來講已經變得很陌生
But we have this speech by Director Lin
但是我們有這個林所長的講演
we may know better
我們可能更貼切了解
Especially when it comes to privacy, privacy, these things.
尤其他牽涉到隱私 隱私權這些事情
I think everyone is very interested
我想大家都興趣很濃厚
then i won't talk nonsense
那我就不多廢話
We now invite Director Lin to welcome Director Lin
我們現在就請林所長 歡迎林所長
Thanks
謝謝
Director Chen and thank you for Huang Feiyuan's introduction just now
陳所長還有謝謝我們的剛才黃飛鴛介紹
Thank you ladies and gentlemen too
也謝謝各位女士 各位先生的
Participate in today's this I want to report to you
參與今天的這個我要跟各位報告的這個
theme
主題
actually, I
其實我
Let's look at these two pictures first
我們先看這兩張圖好了
I actually probably won’t use this slide too much today
我其實是今天大概不會用太多這個slide
Probably the time when the powerpoint was used
大概就是那用的powerpoint的時間
mainly possible
主要是可能
no way to speak or say
沒有辦法用言語講 或者是說
or
或者是說
Because some sharp legal texts will be used in it
因為裡面會用到一些比較尖色的法律的文字
Even if
那怕
It is not easy for everyone to understand what I say in this way
我用這個嘴說的情況的話 大家不容易聽得懂
So it would be possible to use this
所以就可能會用這個
Orpoin, other than that, I'd probably
奧破音 除此之外的話 我大概就會
I really hope that I can talk to you in a relatively simple way.
很希望能夠用比較簡單的方式的話 來跟各位
let's talk
來談
What I am going to talk to you about today in the information society
今天準備跟各位談的資訊社會中的
Privacy and Privacy
隱私跟隱私權
Let's take a look at these two pictures first
都跟我們先看這兩張圖
here is the first
這邊是第一張
sorry
對不起
this is the second
這是第二張
Let's take a closer look at these two
大家再仔細看一下這兩張
I ask everyone to take a look and try this place
我請大家注意看試試看這個地方
If you look at this picture, this place
你看這一張圖的話呢 這個地方
It's just that if only this room looks like it has only one door
就是只有這個房間看起來的話是只有一個門
For the other rooms, he is the same
其他這幾間的話 他是一個通的
look at another one
再看另外這一張
Take a closer look at this one
這張的話 你個人仔細看
every room here every room here
每一個房間的話 這邊每一個房間的話
If he has at least a few rooms, there's only one door.
他起碼有幾個房間的話 只有一扇門
What I want to tell you is that this is what if
我想跟各位講的就是說 這是如果
This is a traditional building in Taiwan
這是我們臺灣的一個傳統的建築
What about these two architectural drawings?
那這兩個建築圖的話
For these two architectural drawings, he
這兩張建築圖的話 他
Basically after the middle of the 19th century
基本上是當時19世紀中夜以後
A design that is probably quite common in Taiwan
在臺灣大概滿普遍的一種設計
If such a design is generally speaking
那這樣子的設計的話 如果從一般來講
words probably
的話 大概
I don't know why they designed it that way
我沒有不曉得當時他們為什麼這麼設計
but
不過
If I read more articles, it might be inside
如果再去看多一點文章的話 大概裡面的話
and
跟
Southern Fujian has something to do with Ke’s buildings
閩南跟克家的建築是有關係
For example, what we just talked about is this
像譬如說我們剛剛講到的是說 這個這樣子的
a building
一個建設
In terms of architectural drawings, it may have something to do with Hakka
建築圖的話 可能跟客家可能有點關係
It was more like
那剛才比較像是
In this picture, he may be with
這張圖的話 他可能是跟
The architectural map of southern Fujian may have something to do with it
閩南的建築圖可能有關係
But I was just saying maybe I
但是我剛才在講說 也許我
My analysis is probably wrong
我的分析是可能是錯的
My analysis may be wrong, just because
我分析可能是錯的 只不過是因為
I because in order to talk about what is privacy
我因為為了要講什麼是隱私
so i brought a tinted glasses
所以我帶了一個有色眼鏡
Look at these two pictures with prejudice
有偏見似的來看這兩張圖
Then when I look at these two pictures, I feel a little happy
那我看這兩張圖的話 就有點劍烈心喜
Say look we can tell you a little bit
說你看我們可以跟各位稍微講一下
Why? Because here we can see
為什麼呢 因為這邊的話 我們可以看出來
In terms of the design of these two pictures, at least as living in this
這兩張圖的設計的話 起碼作為住在這個
People who live inside may feel differently
住在裡面的人 他可能的感覺是不一樣的
If a room then this room
如果一個房間的話 這個房間
There are many places to go in and out
有很多地方都可以進出
Not only like our current society
不是只有像我們現在目前社會
In most homes, if it is your own room
大部分家裡面的話 如果是自己的房間
my room with my spouse
自己跟我配偶的房間
If you are not married today
那如果今天不是還沒有結婚
not yet married
還沒有成家
I live with my parents
我是住在跟父母在一起的話
children or children
小朋友或者是小孩子
I also hope that everyone wants to have a separate room for themselves
也希望個人都希望自己有一個單獨的房間
what do you mean by separate room
所謂單獨的房間是什麼意思呢
A separate room is just one door
單獨的房間就是只有一扇門
And what about this door?
而這扇門的話呢
i can control
我是可以控制的
should i invite people in
我要不要邀請人家進來
But you can imagine
可是各位可以想像出來說
If you live in one room
如果住在一個房間裡面的話
many doors
是很多門
what if i live in it
那我住在裡面的話呢
live in a place where i can control the door
跟住在一個我可以控制門的
It's different in this case
這情況的話是不太一樣的
but i just said
不過我剛才講說
i could be wrong
我可能是錯的
I may be reading it wrong
我可能解讀是錯的
The reason my interpretation might be wrong is because
我的解讀可能是錯的原因是因為
I look at something like this with colored eyes
我帶著有色的眼光來看這樣子的一件事情
But suppose I'm wrong
不過假設我是錯的
it doesn't matter
也沒有關係
Actually, I want to tell you this from the very beginning.
其實我想一開始就跟各位講這件事情
like this
是這樣子的
if
如果
if we think
如果我們認為
What about his privacy?
他隱私的話呢
we will proceed
我們就進行
Basic understanding, what about privacy?
基本的了解 認為隱私的話呢
Is a minimum if in terms of space design
是一個最起碼如果在空間設計上來講
If there should be a space that I can control
應該有一個我自己可以控制的空間的話
What do these two pictures represent?
那這兩張圖所代表出來的意思
maybe not the same
可能就不太相同
But I also have to tell you
但是我也必須跟各位說
it doesn't mean to say
這並不表示說
designed like this
這樣子設計的
It has no concept of privacy
它就沒有隱私的觀念了
maybe it's just something
也許只是什麼呢
we all have because my thoughts are
我們都有 因為我的想法是
based on each society
基於每一個社會
Every society has a concept of privacy
每一個社會都有隱私的觀念
that's just saying
那只不過是說呢
What about in a different society or in the same society?
在不同的社會或同一個社會的話呢
In different times
在不同的時間
content that may be private
可能對於隱私的內容
may not be the same
可能不太相同
That's why we said, in fact, everyone, I just talked about it at the beginning
那所以我們說 其實各位我剛才一開始有講
Design drawings of the two rooms
這兩張房間的設計圖
In fact, it was probably after the middle of the 19th century.
其實是在大概是19世紀中夜以後的
The general architecture in Taiwan looks like this
在台灣的大致上的建築就是這個樣子
what does that mean
那就表示是什麼呢
means that at the same time we exist
就表示在同時間我們存在著
This kind of house with two designs
這樣子兩種設計的房子
that doesn't mean
那並不表示是說
Only their words have privacy
只有他們的話還有隱私
there is no privacy
這種的話就沒有隱私
not like this
並不是這樣子
but what
而是什麼呢
maybe they are different
可能他們不同的
For private content
對於隱私的內容
may think differently
可能有不同的想法
Guys, think again
各位你再想想看
That just talked to the vice president
那剛剛跟副院長
just chatting
剛才在聊
We had a conversation with the vice president this year
我們今年出了話跟副院長
go to italy
到義大利去
When we got to Italy we went to Florins
到義大利的時候我們到Florins
The one from Florins
Florins的那個
what i forgot was that it belonged to the lord
我忘掉的是那個是那個領主的
He later became a museum
他後來變博物館了
if we go to that museum
我們去參加那個博物館的話
you can see that museum
你可以看到那個博物館
Then just keep thinking about that space
然後直接繼續在想那個空間
He is from this room to another room
他是從這個房間到另外的房間
can pass
可以通下去的
Think about it again everyone
各位再想想看你到
been to france
去過法國啦
Germany, Austria
德國啦 奧地利啦
What about these European countries?
這些歐洲的國家的話呢
If we go to that kind of palace
如果我們是到那一種皇宮
or the lord kind
或者是領主的那種
When visiting the building
建築進去參觀的時候
He is now open
他現在目前都開放了
sometimes it has become a museum
有些時候它有變成博物館
Let's think about the space design
大家去想想看那個空間設計
I don't know about the space design
那個空間設計的話不曉得
Just right for our visit now, right?
剛剛好配合我們現在參觀對不對
from this room to another room
從這個房間到另外一個房間
No need to go out again to the hallway
不需要再走出 到走廊
then walk down the corridor
然後從走廊再走去
use a room
利用一個房間
No, but every room is accessible
不需要 但是每個房間都通的
what does this mean
這代表什麼意思
So this is very interesting
所以這個滿有趣的
at the same time
在同時間
that may have been at that time
那個可能是在那個時間
maybe in continental europe
可能是在歐洲大陸的話
their words at the same time
他們同時間的話
It may be for the nobles or the royal family
可能對於貴族或者是皇室來講的話
I think they are very modern
覺得他們那是一個非常Modern的
A design of Fashion
Fashion的一種設計
they don't necessarily think
他們不見得不認為
they may not think that means
他們可能不認為是說
I must have a separate room for each
我一定要每一個單獨的一個房間
It means privacy
才是表示有隱私
probably not the idea
可能不是這個想法
so i just said
所以我剛才只是說
I'm from a biased perspective
我是從帶著偏見的視野
look at something like this
來看這樣子的一個事情
this kind of thing
這種事情的話
I also wanted to tell you
我也想跟過你講
Don't just say that
大家不要就這樣說
they have no privacy
他們就沒有隱私
not privacy
不是隱私
Just look at it with a hard eye
只是帶著一個有偏硬的眼光來看這件事情
maybe they are in this place
也許他們在這個地方
maybe from my point of view
可能從我的觀點來講
They didn't protect the privacy of the person who lived in the room
他們沒有保護那個住在房間裡面的人的隱私
But maybe he has more privacy elsewhere than we do.
但他在別的地方也許比我們還更多的隱私也說不定
so what
所以也是怎麼樣
What about in different societies?
在不同的社會中間的話呢
Although every society has its own concept of privacy
雖然每個社會他都有隱私觀
But what about his private content?
可是他對於那個隱私的內容的話呢
may not be the same
可能是不太相同的
What if I use this example
那我藉這個例子的話呢
Let me tell you about tomorrow
來跟各位說明日說
Actually, I am not talking about architecture with outsiders today.
其實我今天不是跟外來談建築啦
Maybe when it comes to architecture, everyone here may be more suitable to talk about than me.
也許談建築的話可能在座各位都比我更適合來談的問題
Then I just want to understand with you
那我只是跟想跟各位理解
What I mean to explain to you is this
跟各位說明的意思是這樣就是說
Such a study of privacy
對於隱私的這樣一個研究
In fact, it's not just limited to my Chinese law.
其實不是只是限於像我中文法律了
In fact, everyone in society should care about him
其實是應該社會每一個人都應該關心他
His appearance because of privacy
因為隱私他的呈現
We're going to learn about a society at a time
我們要去了解一個社會在一個時間
when was his privacy view
他的隱私觀是什麼時候呢
Actually we
其實我們
There may be a lot to see
可能要看的東西還蠻多的
Not just the so-called counting system at that time
不只是當時的所謂的點賬制度
what does his law say
他的法律什麼規定
or his organizational design
或者是他的有什麼組織設計
Probably more important to look at his life
可能更重要的是要看他的生活
How do they live in normal daily life?
一般日常生活他們是怎麼樣子過的
See them from the midst of his daily life
從他日常生活中間去看他們
what they care what they don't care
他們關心什麼他們沒有關心什麼
Then we can understand
那這樣子我們才能夠了解到
In terms of that society, what they presented at that time
那個社會的話他們當時他所呈現出來的
Where did they put the connotation of privacy?
隱私的那種內涵他們到底放在什麼地方
so i basically
所以我基本上
Although today I want to talk to you about privacy and privacy
雖然今天是要跟各位談隱私隱私權
But I really wanted to tell you from the beginning
但是我一開始就很想跟各位說了
In fact, what I want to talk about today is limited.
其實我今天要講的東西是有限的
I'm just speaking from my lawyer's point of view
我只是從我法律人的觀點來講這件事情
In fact, there may be more that can be cut into the surface
其實可能可以切入面的還更多
Then this study
然後這個研究的話
Because I have been engaged in this research for quite a long time
因為我從事這研究也蠻久的
Then this kind of research
然後這種研究的話
Of course, domestic research is relatively
當然國內的研究還比較
not very hot and weak
不是很熱弱
Then if you read some foreign research
那如果看了一些國外的研究的話
You can see that foreign research is very
大家就可以看到國外的研究非常的
He has a very broad entry point
他從切入點非常的廣
That makes me very envious
那就讓我非常的羨慕
They can come from many places like we just talked about
他們可以從很多的地方 像譬如我們剛剛談到
It's a building they might talk about life
這是一種建築 他們也許會談生活
He looks at it from different places
他從不同的地方切入來看
their society or a certain society
他們那個社會或者某一個社會的
what is that privacy concept
那個隱私觀是什麼
But if you go back to Taiwan and look at our own research in Taiwan
但是如果你回過台來看我們臺灣自己的研究
What about these parts? Relatively speaking, it is relatively
的話呢 這些部分的話呢 相對來講就比較
Few people do research in this area
少人做這方面的研究
So I also hope to say what I said in today's speech.
所以我也蠻希望是說呢 今天的演講的話
able to evoke what you are doing
能夠以喚起各位在做的
interested in this thing
對這個東西有興趣
And then we can look at it from a different perspective, a different perspective
然後我們可以從不同的眼光 不同的視野
or from different scholars
或者從不同的學們
It can be cut into the research that is done, if this is the case
可以切入到是做的這樣的研究 那這樣子的話
we're going to talk about privacy on this
我們對這個要談隱私的話
His content will be richer
他的內容的話就會比較豐富
Then I will do a little bit of my personal research today.
那我今天稍微進一點我個人的研究的
A cut-in from my personal research
從我個人研究的這樣子一個切入
Then go further into some of the results of my research so far
然後越進一些我到目前為止研究的一些成果
I will give you a little report
跟各位稍微做一點報告
let's talk
讓大家來聊
From a lawyer's point of view From my personal point of view as a lawyer
從法律人的觀點 從我個人一個法律人的觀點
When we are doing other legal people
我們在做還有其他的法律人的時候
Not everyone has a different opinion
也沒每個人觀點可能又不太一樣
I'm just speaking from my personal point of view
那我只是從我的個人觀點的話
Let me explain to you
來跟各位來說明
what is privacy what is privacy
什麼是隱私 什麼是隱私權
then what happened to it now
然後呢 它現在發生了些什麼事情
Now it's the consulting society
那現在的話就是諮詢社會
what happened in the middle of the consulting society
在諮詢社會中間發生了什麼事情
What about these things? From the legal person's point of view
那這些事情的話呢 如果從法律人的觀點
From my point of view as a lawyer
從我一個法律人的觀點切入來看的話
Why do you think the current law
為什麼會覺得現在的法律
the current rule of law on privacy
就是目前的有關隱私權的法治
There are deficiencies in the legal norms
法律的規範的話有不足之處
then what we say about such things
那我們對這樣的事情的話
how should
到底怎麼應該
how to look at such a thing
要怎麼來看這樣的事情
That's probably what I'm going to talk to you about today.
今天這大概就是我準備跟各位來談的
wait a minute
這個這個等一下
Talk to us about privacy first
先跟我們談隱私
That
那
I'm offering you a
我在跟提供各位一個
one
一個
you may not have noticed
大家也許沒有注意到
Everyone, let's talk about privacy first.
大家先目前大家講隱私
everyone talks about privacy
每個人都在講隱私
if talking about privacy
如果在講隱私的話
you can think of
你就可以想到
privacy
隱私
May be Privacy
可能就是Privacy
Outside Privacy
Privacy外
or Privacy
或者是Privacy
or a different way of thinking
或者是不同的念法
But it's Privacy
可是就是Privacy
That
那
why does it make me feel like saying
為什麼會讓我會覺得說
This Privacy translates into privacy
這個Privacy翻成隱私
Or privacy is to do Privacy
或者隱私就是要做Privacy
has a problem
有問題
because if i
是因為我如果
If all of us can understand
如果我們各位能夠理解到
It means our Jingling
是說我們的靜靈
statue japan
像日本
or Korea
或者是韓國
same with
同樣是
Words in the middle of traditional culture, society and culture
傳統文化社會文化中間的話
is subject to
是受到
probably influenced by our culture
大概我們的文化影響的
The source is about the same
來源大概差不多
But the words of their society are strange
但是他們這個社會的話很奇怪
When they also encounter Privacy
他們同樣碰到Privacy的時候
They didn't translate it into an equivalent word in Japanese
他們並沒有把它翻成日文的一個相對應的字
Korean is the same no
韓文也一樣 沒有
relatively speaking
相對來講的話呢
They used the so-called foreign language
他們是用了所謂的外來語
What about his words in his pinyin?
他用他的拼音文字的話呢
Go and translate that Privacy into
去把那個Privacy翻成
spelled his Japanese
拼成他的那個日文
or in Korean
或者拼成韓文
relatively strange
相對來講奇怪啦
Then why do we translate Privacy into privacy in Taiwan?
那我們台灣為什麼就把Privacy翻成隱私
Hong Kong turned it into private printing
香港把它翻成私印
What about mainland China and Macau?
中國大陸的跟澳門的話呢
all turned into privacy
都翻成隱私
it's weird
這蠻奇怪的
In the Chinese world
就是在中文世界的話呢
we will say categorically
我們就很意然決然說
we just have
我們就是有
In the middle of Chinese, there are words that can
在中文中間就是有字可以
To show that it is equivalent to this Privacy
來表示跟這個Privacy是相當的
same
同樣的
in Japan or in Korea
在日本或者在韓國
why didn't they do something like this
為什麼他們並沒有做這樣子的事情
why is it like this
為什麼是這樣
Are we starting to touch
是不是我們開始接觸到
When the word Privacy
Privacy這個字的時候
When we are going to translate it into Chinese
我們要把它翻成中文的時候
China at that time
我們當時的那些中國
Chinese
中文
What about in our Chinese world?
在我們中文世界的話呢
In fact, there are corresponding words
其實有相應的詞
It corresponds to this Privacy
是跟這個Privacy是相對應的
So we apply it
所以我們就把它套用過來
is it so
是不是如此
This is what caused me to
這是引發起我對於
why this
這個為什麼要
one reason to study him
要研究他的一個原因
Of course through this
當然透過這樣子的話
we can go up slowly
我們可以慢慢在往上再走
I was talking just now
就剛才在談是說呢
because every society
因為每個社會的話
He has a concept of privacy
他都有隱私的觀念
So by saying like this
所以藉由這樣子的話呢
In fact, if we understand that
其實如果我們理解到的是說
This Privacy is equal to privacy
這個Privacy就等於隱私
Then we also want to pass
那我們也很想透過
What about the word privacy?
隱私這兩個字的話呢
to see in our traditional society
去看看在我們傳統社會
so far
到現在來講的話
What is our view on privacy
我們的隱私觀是什麼
What is our view on this privacy
我們對於這個隱私觀是什麼
I also want to
這也是想
in this regard
在這方面的時候呢
also want to do a little research
也想做一點研究
But first I can tell you some conclusions
但是我先可以跟各位講一點結論
because the process is not over yet
因為這個過程還沒結束
Because the process is quite long
因為這個過程還蠻長的
There is a way to talk to you like this, if you talk like this, everyone may not be interested
有辦法跟各位這樣講 這樣講的話 大家也不見得有興趣
but
不過
From the middle of this kind of research, I just talked about this
從這樣子的研究中間的話 我剛才在講這
Especially when I saw the words of the vice president here, I said
尤其我看到副院長在這邊的話 我人講說
I am from a lawyer's point of view
我是從法律人觀點
I'm not from a historian's point of view so the middle of the report
我不是從歷史學家的觀點 所以報告中間
If you think history is not interpreted this way, please tell me too
如果你覺得是歷史學 不是這樣解釋的話 也請你告訴我
Then this will involve, in fact, there are also linguistic issues in it.
那這裡面就會牽涉到 其實也有語言學的問題在裡面
In addition to the historical linguistics just mentioned, if we
除了剛才講到的史學語言學 那如果我們再稍微
If it is expanded a bit, sociology and anthropology may both be required.
擴大一點的話 可能對社會學 人類學 可能都應該要
This should be fine
這方面應該都可以
should be able to contribute or should be able to happen
應該都可以有所貢獻 或者應該可以有所發生
I'll start with the conclusion
那我先講結論
We believe
我們認為
We came into contact with the word Privacy at that time
我們當時接觸到Privacy這個字
then turn it into privacy
然後就把它翻成隱私
Because of
是因為
The words of our society at that time were considered to be said
我們當時社會的話 是認為是說
The word "privacy" in the Chinese world
中文世界裡面的這隱私這兩個字
It is corresponding to the Privacy in English
就是相應於英文這個Privacy
I never said it was wrong before
我以前都不會講說這是錯的
In fact, when I first came into contact with
其實在當時一開始接觸到
What about Privacy?
Privacy的時候呢
I so far some of our
我到現在為止我們的一些
I have done some analysis so far
搜索到現在做了一些分析
Did not immediately translate him into privacy
並沒有馬上直接把他翻成隱私
no that's surprising
沒有 這蠻訝異的
This lasted until after the 1970s
這個一直要到1970年代以後
we're just getting started
我們才開始 事實上才開始
Really start to think that privacy can be privacy
真正開始會認為說Privacy就能隱私
Privacy equals Privacy
隱私就等於Privacy
This process is quite a long time
這過程還蠻長的一段時間
does not mean that the middle
並不表示是說這中間
No one treats Privacy as privacy
沒有人把Privacy當作隱私
not like this
不是這樣的
It means that he will become
而是說他會變成變成
when there is no problem
沒有問題的時候
Probably after the 1970s
大概到1970年代以後
at least in taiwan
起碼在台灣
So in order to think about this
所以為了要想這件事情的話
we also did one thing
我們也做了一件事情
let him go
就他去
because to find
因為要去找
just find the earliest
就找當時最早的
to see if anyone found
看看有沒有人當時找到
The earliest Yin-Han dictionary
最早的陰漢字典
then we have to do this
那我們要做這件事情
Just look at the English-Chinese dictionary at that time.
就是去看看當時的英漢字典的話
What does he mean by Privacy in Chinese?
他把Privacy等於中文什麼
What about at the same time?
那同時的話呢
we also want to know
我們也想知道是說
Privacy at that time was in the English-speaking world
那個時候的Privacy在英文世界
words of the english world
英語世界的話
What do they mean by Privacy
他們是把Privacy當作什麼意思
that of course some current words
那當然一些目前的話
what is done is still limited
所做的還是有限
We used Oxford
我們是用了Oxford
His English in Oxford
Oxford的他的那個English
That Dishonernary
那個Dishonernary
what about looking for
找的話呢
We can see that at least in 1900
我們可以看到是起碼在1900年那時候
then we can see
那我們可以看到
they go back to words
他們回溯到以前的話
An Oxford like this
這樣子的一個Oxford
English in Oxford
Oxford的那個English
Words in Dishonernary
Dishonernary裡面的話
When he said the word Privacy
他講Privacy這個字的話
He will say that it is actually from earlier
他會講是說其實是從更早
Thanks
謝謝
that's what they say
他們這樣子講就是說
In fact, what about the word Privacy?
其實Privacy這個字的話呢 如果
from
從
In the middle of the English-speaking world, it was between 191600 and 1700
英文世界中間的話呢 在191600年到1700年
You can probably see that a lot of texts use the word Privacy
大概已經可以看到很多文本都在用Privacy這個字
That includes Sasbija's work
那裡面包括Sasbija的那個他的作品
Also use it like this later
也用到這樣子以後
he used the word
他就用到這個字
Then by 1919, at least after 1700, after 1700
那到1919 起碼在1700年之後 1700年之後
What about this part? Maybe
那這一部分的話呢 可能
Use the word Privacy in the English world
用Privacy 英文世界裡面用Privacy這個字的話
just more and more more and more
就是越來越多 越來越多
So we still don't know when the word "he" first started.
所以我們到目前還不知道說 他最早這個字從什麼時候開始
But at least in 1600 there has been
可是起碼是說 1600年已經有了
What about after 1700?
到1700年以後的話呢
he used the word
他就用了這個字
Then he used the word
然後他就用了這個字
Then he used the word but said it already existed in 1600
那他就用了這個字 但是說1600年已經有了
What about after 1700?
到1700年以後的話呢
This word is probably very common in the English-speaking world.
這個字大概在英語世界的話就非常普遍
That
那
What does the word Privacy mean?
那這個Privacy這個字是什麼意思
According to this Ostford University some of their
那根據這個Ostford University他們的一些
Induction, he thinks he has about six meanings
歸納 他認為他大概有六種意思
But by 1900 they were saying
不過到1900年的時候他們就說
In fact, these six meanings
其實這六種意思的話
If from their analysis
如果從他們的分析的話
I think it refers to the words from 1700 to the present
認為是說在1700年之後到現在的話
By then 1900 words
到當時1900年的話
Probably two meanings
大概就是兩種意思
There are probably only two meanings left
大概只剩下兩種意思
Other words probably have become
其他的話大概就是已經變成是
yes
是
passed
過去了
or no longer commonly used
或者不再常用
Those two meanings are commonly used
那兩種意思他們是常用的
That is to say, it may be a kind of solitary
就是說可能是一種單獨
The state or condition of being out of public notice
不受打擾 不受大眾注意的狀態或條件
is a right to choose
是一種選擇的權利
That's a kind of rejection
那或者是一種格絕
or freedom from interference or intrusion
或者是不受干擾或侵入的自由
this is the first explanation
這是第一種解釋
the second explanation
那第二種解釋的話
is to say
是認為是說
Private or Personal Matters of the First Kind
第一種私人或個人事務
is a secret
是一種秘密
you can understand
那各位可以理解
What about after that?
這樣講完之後的話呢
Probably everyone
大概各位
It may be the word privacy that you first imagined.
可能跟各位先想像的隱私這兩個字
In the middle of your mind now
在現在各位腦海中間
Does it mean this kind of privacy?
是不是也代表這樣的隱私
think about it
大家想想看
each of us mouth
我們每個人嘴巴
Now everyone will talk about
現在目前大家都會講到
This is my privacy
這是我的隱私
when we say this
當我們在講這句話的時候呢
what we think is my privacy
我們認為的這是我的隱私
what is that privacy
那個隱私是什麼隱私
This is not usually according to this Chinese wording
這不通常就照這個中文字眼
just in Chinese
就照中文嘛
don't be so stupid
不要那麼笨
Why do you spend so much time doing research?
花那麼多時間做研究幹什麼
Just follow the literal meaning of Chinese
就直接照中文的字面上意義就好了嘛
It's something I don't want others to know
就是我不想讓別人知道的事情嘛
is it like this
是不是這樣子
In fact, of course, what else is there on the other hand?
其實當然另外一方面還有什麼呢
Just now if you see what you just said
剛剛如果在看到剛才講的
Ospo's his
Ospo的他的那個
words in english language
英文語言的話
what he said
他講的話
he's not just talking about that
他不只是在講那件事情
he also includes space
他也包括空間
I'm a space I don't want people to invade
我是一個不想讓人侵入的空間
Everyone think about the building just mentioned
大家想想看剛才提到的那個建築
that house house
那個房屋房屋
The design of that room of the house
房子的那個房間的設計
the design of that room
那個房間的設計的話
Do you feel
是不是大家會覺得
That kind of fits with my notion of privacy
那個好像有點符合我的隱私的觀念
That said, my view of privacy
那說我的隱私觀的話
Not just saying a lot of things I don't want people to know
不只是說很多事情我不想別人知道
May also include I must have a space
可能也包括我必須要有一個空間
to allow anyone to enter the space
要讓任何人都可以進入的空間
unless invited
除非有邀請
So this may be what you want to see
所以這個可能大家想看
After the 1970s
那時候1970年代以後
Until now, Privacy in English
一直到現在這個英語裡面的Privacy
what about this word
這個字眼的話呢
Is what he explained already a bit like this?
他所解釋的是不是已經有點是這個樣子了
But it's also quite strange
但是也蠻奇怪的就是
What about in the Chinese world?
在中文世界的話呢
what we saw
我們當時一看的話
what we found was looking for that
我們找到的是找那個
Just now I reported to you
剛才也跟各位報告就是說
Let's go find a Yin-Han dictionary
我們一去找陰漢字典
But when looking for a Yin-Han dictionary?
可是找陰漢字典的時候呢
The Yin-Han dictionary does not directly translate Privacy into
陰漢字典並沒有直接把Privacy就翻成
Privacy that everyone takes for granted now is not
現在大家認為理所當然的Privacy沒有
The most common one is to turn Privacy into
最常見到的是可能把Privacy翻成
wet
濕
we'll keep him private
我們就把他搬成隱私
Then it becomes very
那這又變成也很有
Very very strange
很有很奇怪
or interesting
或者是說很有意思
Then I'm cutting in from another angle
那我在從另外一個角度切入
So that you can be more clear what I just said is that
讓各位可以更清楚我剛剛講到的是說
In fact, we now think
其實我們現在認為
Privacy is privacy
Privacy就是隱私
We just flip it over like this
我們就直接就這樣直接翻過來
that's not that fast
那不是那麼的快
A message I got from another legal person
我從另外一個法律人提供的一個訊息
The information provided just now may not be enough
剛才那個提供的訊息可能都不夠
because if anyone is interested
因為如果大家有興趣的話
If today is linguistics
如果今天是語言學的
or literary
或者是文學的
if interested
如果有興趣的話
with more research
再做更多的研究的話
may find out
可能會發覺說
This information is not enough
這資訊還不夠充分
Or even the interpretation of this information is wrong
或者甚至這個資訊的解讀是錯的
that's okay
那沒有關係
I am now offering a view from a legal person
我現在提供一個法律人的一個觀點
What do we think of the legal person?
法律人我們怎麼來看呢
We learn from our legal textbooks
我們從我們法律人的教科書
Let's look at the journal papers
跟期刊論文我們來看
let's see what it means
我們來看看是說
If Privacy is called
如果Privacy就是叫做
From the photographer's words, it stands to reason
影師的話 那照理說
If in our legal person's
如果在我們法律人的
inside this textbook
這個教科書裡面
or in the research we wrote about
或者在我們寫的研究的
What about the words in the middle of the paper?
奇刊論文中間的話呢
when he uses the word
他用到這個字的話
He should be a single shadow teacher right away, right?
他就應該直接就會單身影師嘛 對不對
What does it look like?
結果看起來的話呢
just what i told you
就我跟各位講的
Why talk about the 1970s
為什麼會講說1970年代
probably later
大概之後的話呢
it may be possible to say
可能可以這樣講
It wasn't like this before
之前的話都不是這個樣子
Because
原因是
because we lawyers
因為我們法律人
These textbooks published
所出版的這些教科書
or drill some
或者所鑽一些的
What about the words among the published papers in these odd journals?
出版的這些奇刊論文中間的話呢
messages we found
我們找到的訊息
can see
可以看得到
not like this
不是這個樣子
it's going to be slow
是要慢慢慢慢的
glasses to the end words
眼鏡到最後的話
what did it become
它就變成了什麼呢
become a photographer
變成影師
the early days
早期
earliest
最早
we can see that means
我們可以看到是說呢
if that he wrote that
如果那個他寫的那個
odd journal paper
奇刊論文裡面
or he is in the book
或者他是著作裡面
he us
他我們
The reason why we can know is to say
之所以可以知道是說
In fact, I want to talk about Private
其實是要想講Private
the word
這個字
The reason is because we start with
原因是因為我們從
Let's now look at the materials he used at that time
我們現在來看他當時所要用的資料
information in english
英文的資料
We can tell he wants to use the word Privacy
我們可以知道他想要用Privacy這個字
But then
可是當時的話
first translated words
最早翻譯的話
He didn't translate him as Privacy
他並沒有把他翻成叫做Privacy
turned into privacy
翻成隱私
he turned him into a secret
他把他翻成秘密
turned into a secret
翻成秘密
that turned into a secret
那翻成秘密
Then later words gradually slowly changed from secret
然後後來的話才逐漸慢慢慢慢從秘密
just started to become private
才開始變成隱私
this is very interesting
這個是很有趣的
why is it funny
為什麼很有趣呢
If we start from another entry point
如果我們再從另外一個切入點
We do not start from the word Privacy
我們不從Privacy這個字眼切入
but from
而是從
everyone knows
大家也知道
this
這個
Maybe you are not so clear
也許各位不是那麼清楚
but i can tell you
但是我可以跟各位說
Taiwan's Civil and Criminal Law
台灣的民刑法
Basically
基本上是
Everyone says we are a civil law system
大家就講說我們是大陸法系
Many of you can understand
大家很多人聽得懂
civil law
就是大陸法系
We are not a legal system
我們不是一枚法系
Under the context of the civil law system,
在大陸法系的這樣脈絡之下的話
our in
我們的在
It's in the civil law
就是民法裡面的話
is also subject to
也是受
Logically speaking, it is also a civil law system
照理說也是大陸法系
The legal system is based on this tradition
法系的基於這個傳統
As for the civil law system, there probably is one
那大陸法系裡面的話呢 大概裡面有一個
probably related to the privacy we're going to talk about today
可能跟我們今天要談到的隱私
right of personality
隱私權有關的他是在人格權
personality rights section or torts section
人格權部分 或者是侵權行為部分
Then we go to the early
那這樣我們就去找早期的
Textbook of Civil Law
民法的教科書
As for the civil law textbooks, at the earliest time, of course we
那民法教科書的話 最早的時候呢 我們當然
Just find Mr. Shi Changhuan, and then become a possible legal person
就找到史昌歡先生的 再做可能法律人的話
Mr. Shi Changhuan
就知道史昌歡先生
That Mr. Shi Changhuan first used
那史昌歡先生他最早用到的
in his textbook
他的那個教科書裡面
What about the words in his textbook? He is using
他教科書裡面的話呢 他在用
In the
在在
In fact, he wants to explain what personality rights are
其實他是想說明什麼叫人格權
or infringement
或者侵權行為裡面的
The part that infringes on personality rights
那個侵害人格權的部分
As a result, two words suddenly appeared in him.
結果呢 他裡面就把他裡面突然間出現兩個字
is a secret
就是秘密
secret
秘密
He just said something in the middle of this type of human rights violation
他就說在這個侵害人權類型中間的話呢
there are secrets in it
有包含秘密在裡面
The word secret is actually the same as
秘密這兩個字的話呢 其實就跟
if we say this
如果我們這樣講
It's actually the same as the privacy we're going to talk about today.
跟今天要談的隱私其實就是一樣的
But they're called secrets
可是他們就叫做祕密
So on the other hand
所以從另外一方面的話
We can see another tradition
我們可以看到另外一個傳統
That is the tradition of the civil law system
那個是大陸法系的傳統
traditional words in civil law systems
大陸法系的傳統的話
speaks this part of german
是講德國的這一部分
words in this part of germany
德國這一部分的話
I have to tell you here too
這邊也必須要跟各位講
Today we talk about privacy called Privacy
我們今天講說隱私就叫Privacy
Privacy is privacy
Privacy就是隱私
But when we say
但是我們在這樣講的時候
It's Privacy under the English-speaking world
是在英語世界之下的Privacy
Let me tell you a little bit more
那各位再跟各位稍微再講一點就是
In fact, the word Privacy
其實Privacy這個字的話
in german or in french
在德文或者在法文
At least the one I asked didn't have the same word
起碼我問到的沒有相同的字
no same word
沒有相同的字
Of course they express it in other ways
當然他們用別的方式來表示
same concept
相同的概念
so today we
所以我們今天
Strange
奇怪了
I mean Taiwan
就是說台灣啊
Mainland China
中國大陸啦
Hong Kong
香港啦
Macau
澳門啦
South Korea
韓國啦
south korea
南韓啊
Or use Privacy in Japan
或者日本都用Privacy
Privacy is used in many places
很多地方都用Privacy
then directly
然後就直接
adopted the traditions directly from here
直接從這邊接受了這邊的傳統
Traditions on the side of Anglo-American law
英美法這邊的傳統
The traditional words of German law become another
德國法這邊傳統的話就變成另外一個
But here the words are in this
但是在這邊的話在這個
The words on this, this, this topic, on this topic
這個這個這個topic上面 在這個議題上面的話
The last thing we saw was a stream
我們最後看到是一個會流
Meeting stream becomes a privacy again
會流又變成了一個隱私
So let's look at what we just talked about
所以我們看剛才談到的
from if from this civil law system
從如果從這個大陸法系的
If German law comes here
如果德國法這邊過來的話
it's a secret
它是講秘密秘密
What about the last word?
到最後的話呢
Slowly it turns into privacy
慢慢慢慢它就轉成隱私了
over here
這邊呢
we just started talking about
我們剛才開始講到說
We see that originally it was meant to say
我們看到原先它是要講
The relevant information of the word Privacy
Privacy這個字的那個相關的資料
The words about these things come from Anglo-American law.
講這些東西的話是從英美法這樣過來的
What about here?
那這邊的話呢
In fact, Anglo-American law may be too broad
其實英美法也許太廣了
It should be about American law.
應該講美國法這邊過來的
What about over here?
那這邊過來的話呢
Privacy was originally translated as secret
Privacy原先翻成秘密
why it turned into a secret
它之所以翻成秘密
Is it because when the time was 1950
是不是因為當時間1950
In the 1940s, 1950s, and 1960s
40年代1950年代1960年代的時候呢
In fact, in our legal circle
其實在我們法律圈子裡面
So in terms of that related concept, I think he is going to
所以於那個相關的概念的話 會認為他是要做
secret
祕密
But then slowly it became private
可是後來慢慢慢慢的就轉成了隱私
It's a fun place to say I can't help it
這地方很有趣 地方就在於說 我沒有辦法
find more
再找到更
Let me explain with more information
更其他的資料再來說明說
Why was it 1960s and 70s, especially that
為什麼那時候1960代70年代 特別是那個
Why did that transformation in the 1970s start to become
70年代那個轉變 為什麼開始變成是
used to tell secrets
以前講祕密
So why now suddenly we need to use another
那現在為什麼突然間我們需要用到另外一個
The word called privacy to replace the secret?
詞叫做隱私來取代這個祕密呢
not sure
不太清楚
However, if the media
不過如果跟媒體
It's what journalism scholars and communication scholars talk about
就是新聞學者 傳播學者他們談的話
They feel that the credit is on their side and cannot be credited.
他們就覺得功勞在他們那邊 不能講功勞
That is to say, I will watch it at that time
就是說 那時間的話再去看
That was the time when newspapers and magazines, they started more
那是報紙雜誌的時候 他們比較多都開始
reporting some
在報導一些
foreign news, foreign news inside
國外的新聞的時候 國外新聞裡面的話
Perhaps the most reported ones are probably the news from the United States.
可能報導比較多的是 可能美國的新聞
There may be more words in the news, just like now
那新聞裡面的話 可能比較多的 就像現在
At present, it may be that some societies
目前的 可能比較多都是一些社會
or some
或者一些
Some news about some famous people and politicians
一些有名的人的政治人物的一些新聞
If it involves news about politicians and famous people
那涉及到政治人物有名的人的新聞的話
What must everyone want to see more?
大家會比較想看的一定就是什麼呢
It may be related to his Privacy
可能跟他Privacy有關的
If he got it over here
那這邊他弄過來的話
Maybe they just turned it into Privacy
說不定就是變成他們就把它翻成叫做Privacy
maybe it means
說不定就認為是說
The word Privacy is translated into secret words
這個Privacy這個字翻成秘密的話
Maybe they got it over there
可能就他們那邊弄過來的話
they don't think it's enough
他們覺得不夠
not enough
不夠
when you're just telling a secret
你單純是講秘密的時候
They will feel that telling the secret should be an understanding
他們會覺得說這個秘密應該就是一個理解
like this
是這個樣子
But what about privacy?
可是隱私的話呢
Maybe his scope is a little bit more than secret
可能他的範圍又稍微比秘密要再多一點
we are not sure
我們不確定
so let's go back and see
所以我們再回去再來看看
In fact, the word privacy
其實這個隱私這兩個字
words in the chinese world
在中文世界的話
What about in our traditional culture?
在我們傳統文化中間的話呢
Is there any way we can find these two words
我們有沒有辦法找到這兩個字
what does he mean
他的意思是什麼
Then we can see that the earliest words
那我們可以看到其實最早的話呢
The two words "hidden" and "lost" were separated very early
隱跟失這兩個字分別很早
Appeared very early in the Chinese world
在中文世界就很早就出現
But what if these two words are connected together?
但是這兩個字要連接在一起的話呢
exist
在
It was mentioned in the Spring and Autumn Period of the Warring States Period
戰國時期的那個與世春秋裡面有提到
But it's funny when he mentions it. He's called
不過他提到的時候呢很有趣 他叫做
the winner wins or loses
贏者 贏呢 失也
win or lose
贏呢 失也
What does it mean? What is winning means losing?
意思又是什麼呢 什麼叫做贏 也就是失啊
That's the two words? He seems to agree.
那就是這兩個字呢 他好像是同意的
agree
是同意的
But he changed these two words into saying win or lose
可是這兩個字他變成把他變成說 贏失
he called win
他叫贏
lost too
失也
So he is using
所以他是用
to explain what
來解釋什麼
What is winning and losing?
什麼叫做贏 還有就是失啊
just win
就是贏
That
那
If we go to the instructions to explain
如果我們到說明解釋
When it comes to the explanation and explanation, let’s look at the explanation and explanation of Xu Sheng in the Eastern Han Dynasty
到說明解釋的部分的話 我們再去看到東漢時期的許勝他的說明解釋
He came down from the front and down to him, at least up to the word he understood until then
他從前面再就下來 到他 起碼到那他在那時候為止他所理解的那個字
He also didn't combine winning with losing half
他也沒有把贏跟失兩分之一在一起
At most, he just talked about winning and losing.
他頂多也就是講到說贏失也
what is he talking about at most? what is he talking about at most?
最多的話 他是在講什麼呢 他最多是在講字說
In fact, what are the words called?
事實上來講的話都是叫做什麼
just cover one up
就是把一個遮掩起來
It's called shadow
掩蓋起來這叫影
But apart from this more usual awareness
但是除了這個比較通常的意識之外的話
In addition, there are about thirty other consciousnesses.
另外大概還有三十幾種的意識
shadow meaning
影的意思
However, the consciousness that has the most wishes for shadow names and names is shadows.
可是影名名願最多的一個意識就是影
private eye
私眼
Then this has been like this since the Warring States Period
那這個就從戰國時期的話就有這樣子
If you really want to connect these two words together
那如果真正要把這兩個字連在一起
The information we have found so far
我們到目前找到的資料的話
I can only see that it was in the Northern and Southern Dynasties
也只看到是在南北朝
during the two dynasties
兩朝的時候
a word we see
我們看到的一個詞
Should it be about the father or the word
那個應該是講父還是詞
a word is used in it
裡面用到了一個字
The two words called "shadow private" are connected together
叫影私這兩字連在一起
But at that time
可是在講那個時候
Let's look at the time when the two words are connected together
我們再去看兩個字連在一起的時候
what is its consciousness
它的意識是什麼呢
Consciousness is talking about husband and wife
意識是在講夫妻兩個人
something in the middle of defense
在規防中間的事
Call shadow private
叫影私
other than this
除了這個之外的話
If we do some more analysis
我們再做一些分析的話
we can probably see
我們大概可以看得出來
except us
除了我們
just talked about this
剛剛講到了這個
this
這個
that is, between husband and wife
就是說夫妻之間的
These situations between men and women
男女之間的這些情勢
called privacy
叫做隱私之外
Then there are probably two more, and three others. There are four in total.
那大概還有兩種 還有其他三種 一共有四種
We all seem more common
我們大家看起來比較普遍的
If we count
如果我們統計到
at least to
起碼到
Late Qing Dynasty 190 19
清末190 19
It is equal to the mid-19th century in the late Qing Dynasty
就是等於清末19世紀中期
Let's see what's going on in the middle, except what I just said
這中間的話 我們大家看 除了剛才講到的
there is another
還有另外一個
dark secret
具有負面意義不可告人的秘密
My secret is also called privacy
我不可告人之秘 也叫隱私
The third kind of words, he does not have any positive
那第三種的話 他是不具有任何正面
or the secret of negative reviews
或是負面的評價的秘密
secret
秘密
As for the fourth type, there are actually more of them.
那第四種的話 其實是比較多的 這個
as long as it raises something that might be worth discussing
只要引起可能比較值得討論的
He is a clean person, we often talk about it when we see it
他就是潔人隱私 我們看到常常就講
Clean privacy Clean privacy
潔人隱私 潔人隱私
But when we watch him clean his privacy, we pay attention
可是看他潔人隱私的時候 我們注意
at that time
那時候
What words do you use?
用的字眼的話呢
Its privacy is related to privacy
它那個隱私是跟隱私
cloudy cloudy
陰天的陰
Yin and private two are used at the same time
陰私兩個是同用的
So this privacy and privacy
所以這個隱私跟陰私
Everyone thinks of what privacy and privacy mean to you
大家想到陰私跟隱私對你們來講的話
what's your impression
你們的觀感是什麼
Is insidiousness more negative?
陰私會不會比較負面
privacy seems like
隱私好像就好像
It seems nothing special
好像都沒有特別
But tell me
可是跟各位講說在
until at least
到起碼在
When we come into contact with the word Privacy
我們在接觸Privacy這個字的時候
There's nothing wrong with having privacy back then
那時候有隱私沒有錯
also have privacy
也有隱私
And privacy and privacy are used together
而且隱私跟隱私它是同用的
Then we can also see
那我們也可以看到
If it will continue to develop at the end of the Qing Dynasty
清末它將繼續發展的話
to the Republic of China
到民國的時候
Also these two words are also in our newspaper
也這個兩個字也是在我們的報紙上
or even on paperwork
或者是甚至在公文書上
I have seen the word privacy
都有看到隱私這兩個字
So we can understand that by saying
所以我們可以理解到說
When the word Privacy was introduced
Privacy這個字引進來的時候
Actually at that time
其實那個時候
And we have no privacy for these two Chinese words
並我們對沒有隱私這兩個中文詞
the word of these two words
這兩個字的這個詞
Existed at that time, not non-existent
當時是存在的 不是不存在的
So it's also strange that he didn't
所以也很奇怪當時他並沒有當時要把
PrivacyTranslate to this
Privacy翻成這個
When speaking Chinese, he did not choose
這個中文的時候 他並沒有先選用
privacy that already existed
當時其實已經存在的隱私
So it's also an interesting one
所以這也是一個很有趣的一個
why is it like this
為什麼是這個樣子
It is also worth our continued thinking
也是值得我們再繼續去想的
But what I wanted to tell you just now is to say
不過我剛才想跟各位講到就是說
whether he is
不管他是
even then
即便當時
Or that I just researched
或者是說我剛才研究
is wrong
是錯的
Anyway, Privacy turned over is privacy
反正Privacy翻過來就是隱私
This privacy word is literally
這個隱私的話就照字面上來講的
I just don't want others to know
就是不想讓別人知道的一些
private matter
私人的事情
plus a little personal space
再加上一點私人的空間
Then this word is the same as the word Privacy in English at that time
那這個的話跟英文的Privacy那時候的字
Even now the word is actually the same
甚至到現在的那個字都其實是一樣的
Even though I just said that even if we have the same
即便 我剛才講說即便我們有同樣的
concept
概念
In fact, if you look at the wisdom of Chinese
其實如果看中文的智慧
over there privacy or privacy
那邊的隱私或者隱私
or secret or something
或者是秘密或者是什麼
In fact, we all have the concept of privacy
其實我們都有隱私的概念
It's just that we may not be useful
只不過我們可能沒有用
Privacy as everyone understands it now
現在大家所理解的Privacy
that subfield also describes it
那個字區也描述它
Then we might have to explain to you
那我們可能要跟各位說明
Even if we use the same words now
即便我們用了現在同樣的字眼
called privacy
叫做隱私
But you have to understand
但是各位要瞭解到是說
even with the same word
即便同樣的字眼
its at different times
它在不同的時期
or in different societies
或者在不同社會
The reason why it advocates the concept of privacy
它之所以會主張隱私這個概念
Its possible function and purpose
它可能的功能跟目的
may not be exactly the same
可能不完全相同
so our
所以我們的
Huang Kewu who entered the teacher's institute
進師所的黃克武
Director Huang once did some research
黃所長他曾經就做了一些研究
I think he's a study
我覺得他一個研究
In the end he said something that said
他最後他講到一些就是說
Actually even though we have the same noun
其實即便我們有相同的那個名詞
but
但是呢
content of the concept
這個概念的內容
Especially from its function and purpose
特別是從它的功能跟目的
if it goes in
它進去的話
We can see that it is actually different
我們可以發覺它其實是不同的
Especially when it comes to privacy
特別在隱私這一塊的話
our privacy
我們隱私這一塊的話
Maybe it's just saying that I don't want others to know
可能只是單純說我不想讓別人知道
I don't want people in my space
我不想讓別人進來我的空間
But if we can learn
但是如果我們可以了解到
Said that we will go to see this matter again today
說今天我們再去看這件事情的話
You may not simply say
大家可能不是單單純純說
I don't want others to know
我不想讓別人知道
I don't want anyone to know come in
我不想讓別人知道進來
And maybe when we say these words
而可能我們在講這些字眼的時候
In fact, there is another meaning
其實還有另外一個含義
that is the modern sense
那就是現代意義的
It's just that there may be some individualistic concepts coming in.
就是可能有一些個人主義的觀念進來了
that early words
那早期的話
Maybe it doesn't have that idea
可能它沒有那個觀念
The idea that it changes is over there
它變變的那個觀念在那邊
it simply says
它只是單純的說
I don't want others to know
我不想讓別人知道
But is there a behind it
可是它後面有沒有一個
modern sense
現代意義的
The reason why I don't want others to know
之所以不想讓別人知道
don't want to make others angry
不想讓別人侵怒
In fact, he has a very positive meaning
其實他有一個很積極的意思
That positive means
那個積極的意思就是說
this is what i want to prove
這是我想要證明
i am an autonomous
我是一個自主
self-determining
可以決定自主決定的
i can be the one who chooses
我可以做選擇的人
In this case maybe
這個情況的話可能
That meaning may not have been in the early days
那個意思再早期可能是沒有
I don't know if you guys are thinking about privacy right now
我不曉得現在各位在想隱私
this is my privacy time
這是我的隱私的時候
When you say this word
各位在講這個字眼的時候
Apart from saying that this is the standby of the warm knife
背後除了是說這是溫刀的待機
this is mine
這是我個人的
This is my space, you don't come in, you don't care about these things
這是我的空間你不要進來你不要管這些事情
It's a matter of asking people to take care of it or not
叫人要不要管的這個事情
other than this
除了這之外的話
do you have another meaning
有沒有另外一個意思
This is my business
這是我當家做主的事情
After this, I will be able to prove that
後過這樣子的話我才能夠再證明說
I am an individual that exists alone and meaningfully
我是一個單獨存在有意義存在的一個個體
Does it mean something like this
是不是有這樣子的意思
If I want to talk to you today about the concept of privacy, I want to tell you
今天想要跟各位講從隱私的概念的話要跟各位
In this way, I mainly want to tell you what I mean.
這樣講下來主要是跟各位想講的意思就是說
Actually we are talking about privacy today
其實我們今天在講隱私
Privacy may be related to this Privacy
隱私也許跟這個Privacy
the original English word
原先這個英文的詞
the word in the world
世界裡面的這個詞
modern meaning
它所講表示的現代的意義
about the same
大概都差不多
So Chinese choose to use privacy
所以中文選擇用隱私
Seems to be pretty good
好像也還滿好的
it also satisfies
它也滿符合
Literally interpreted from simplicity, it is very similar
從單純中字面上去解釋的話很像
it's my private matter
就是我個人的私密的事情
My personal affairs don't need your intervention
我個人的事情不需要你來干預
Then let's add a little space concept into it.
那我們再加上一點空間的觀念進去
besides things
除了事情之外
what else is there room
還有什麼 還有空間
my space
我的空間
the size of this space
這空間大小
maybe it's because
可能是在於是說
The Contest I was in
我所處的那個Contest
when the environment was different
那個環境不同的時候
that maybe the size of that space
那個可能那個空間的大小
may be a little different
可能會有點不同
everyone can understand
大家可以理解
If it is here today, it is very urgent on the MRT
今天如果是在這個在捷運上非常急
Of course there is no way to talk about that space
那個空間當然就沒有辦法講說
don't get too close to me
你不要跟我太近
if you get too close
靠近我太近的話
Just invade my privacy, probably not
就侵害我隱私 大概不會
But if it's a very large space
但如果是一個非常大的空間
of course of course
當然當然
What are you doing so close to your official document?
你公文那麼近幹什麼
Why are the official documents so intimate?
那公文那麼親密幹什麼
You'll feel like there's a difference between
你會覺得這中間就會有差別
He said he was a relative concept
他說他是一個相對性的概念
But the words here are worth thinking about again.
但是這邊的話也很值得我們再去思考一個問題
It is very worthwhile for us to think about a question that is
非常值得我們去思考一個問題就是說
Why does every society have some concept of so-called privacy
為什麼每個社會他都會有一些所謂的隱私的概念
The content of this privacy may not be complete
這個隱私的內容可能不完全
very specific may not be exactly the same
很具體的可能不完全相同
For example, often
譬如是說常常就會
We often meet some new friends
我們常常就碰到一些新認識的朋友
will always want to say
就會常常想說
I'm curious
我很好奇喔
how do you stay so young
你怎麼保持那麼青春
you're probably only 18
你大概只有18歲吧
start asking people's age
就開始問人家年齡
Wow you look like you are very accomplished
哇你這個看起來說你這個成就很有成就
how much money do you make every month
那你每個月賺多少錢
Then this may be in some societies
那這個可能在有些社會
He doesn't think it's offensive
他不會覺得說這是很侵犯別人
But in some societies
但是在有些社會的話
I thought how could it be like this
就覺得說怎麼可以這樣子
it's none of your business
這不關你的事情
so the details
所以很細節的部分
Just do what you don't want others to know
就做於說哪些事情不欲人知
we think it's reasonable
我們覺得很合理
What things in that society feel to say
哪些事情在那個社會覺得說
it's no big deal
這沒什麼大不了的
so you'll notice
所以你會發覺到
What about the very details?
非常細節的部分的話呢
maybe it will be different
可能它就會有也不同
So this also aroused my curiosity to say
所以這也引起我的好奇是說
How could it be like this?
怎麼會是這個樣子呢
Then let's think about another question slowly.
那我們慢慢就去想另外的一個問題
That
那
Time is limited, I can simply use one word
時間有限我就很簡單用一個詞
One sentence in the middle of Lun
倫語中間的一句話就講
it just talks
它就講說
non-gift event
非禮物動會
Non-gift story, non-gift is non-gift
非禮物物言非禮物是非禮物物聽
I can't sort it out like this
類似像這樣子那個排序我沒有辦法排出來
maybe our
可能我們的
Modern fathers and sons who are afraid of old people can be excreted
現代的恐老父子大家可以排出來
what should be a gift
應該是什麼非禮物
Audio-visual serious audio-visual serious OK great
視聽嚴重視聽嚴重OK太好了
Probably everyone can know this, if you are in
大概有大家可以知道這個那你如果在
In the western world, it can be seen as a water monkey
在西方世界的話就可以看到是水 monkey
Right or wrong?
對不對就含就是
Mouth arms covered
嘴巴臂遮起來
Actually I think it's a good example
其實我覺得這是一個很好的例子
This is in the middle of the Analects
這個是在論語中間的話呢
Empty words are not a thing he has said come out
空話不是他已經講的一個東西出來
It means that people may be in the middle of interaction
就是人與人之間可能在互動中間的話呢
He has at least one minimum thing
他起碼有一個最起碼的東西
His so-called unreasonable is not telling us not to see and not to listen
他所謂非理並不是叫我們說不要去看不要聽的
It's a matter of reason
而是那個理的問題
Does it make sense?
合不合那個理
That reason may be that society
那個理可能是那個社會
Or the middle of his ideal society?
或者是他理想中的社會中間的話呢
what is
是什麼
Everyone should give respect to others
每個人之間應該給予別人的尊重
there is a divide over there
有一個分際在那邊
So we're going to continue our research
所以我們就要去再繼續研究的話
you will talk
你就會講說
What about every society?
每個社會的話呢
What about the formation of his concept of privacy?
他的隱私概念的形成的話呢
Will follow the so-called social norms of the society at that time
會跟他當時的社會的所謂的social norms
English is called social norms
英文的裡面叫social norms
Then we translate it into words
那我們把它翻成的話
may be related to the social norms of the time
可能跟當時的社會規範
may be related
可能有點關係
Maybe it has something to do with some morals in a society
可能跟一個社會裡面一些道德
some notions of value
一些價值的觀念
may be related
可能是有關係的
what about these words
那這些的話呢
It may also be due to some time
也可能會因為時間的一些
this
這個
What about different or social changes?
不同或者是社會的變遷的話呢
he may have something different
他可能會有些不同的內容
So we might as well understand this
所以我們可能也要理解到這個
When we want to understand our society
當我們要去了解我們這個社會
What about the concept of privacy in our society?
我們這個社會的隱私的觀的時候呢
In fact, we should be curious people to understand
其實我們就應該很好奇的人來了解
most of our society
我們這個社會大多數的人
There should be at least a division between people
對於人際之間應該最起碼的一個分際
where is it
是在哪邊
how do we see
我們是怎麼樣來看
that this morning
那今天早上
we hired a
我們請了一位
calligraphic calligraphy and painting art workers
書法的書畫的藝術工作者
also a guru
也是一個大師
Mr. Zhu Zhennan went to our so-called speech
朱振南先生到我們所謂的去演講
Then what he said was
那他講的題目就是說
Outsiders can't
人外無法
Then he was talking about a
然後他在談一個
That is to say, an interaction between our art and law
就是說我們的藝術跟法學之間的一個互動
one thing he said
他講的一件事情
Then I said that when he talked about this matter, he was very
然後我就說他講這件事情他非常
He wondered how the society has come to this level
他就覺得這個社會怎麼到這個程度
He feels very aura
他非常覺得很有點氣場
then I will talk to civilization
那我就跟文明
The deputy director said, very good, this is what I can talk about today.
副所長講說 很好 這個是我今天可以講的
A thing
一個東西
what did he say
他講了什麼
He said that recently, everyone understands that it is not often
他講最近 大家理解最近不是常常
This court thinks that
這個法院覺得是說
There are too many reports of violations in this report case
這個檢舉案件的這種違規檢舉案太多
Right? Then why are there so many reported cases?
對不對 那為什麼檢舉案件那麼多
It means that the police transferred a lot, so why did the police transfer
就是警察移送了很多 那警察為什麼會移送
There are so many because of why many people sue
那麼多呢 就是因為什麼呢 很多人告
many people report
很多人檢舉
What about now? In our society now
那現在怎麼樣呢 現在我們社會中間的話
There are many enthusiastic
有很多很熱心的
But on the other hand, it is also possible that our law-breakers encourage such enthusiasm
但是另外一方面的話 也有可能是我們的法規犯去鼓勵這樣子的熱心
So he started going around to report some things he couldn't get used to.
就開始到處去檢舉一些他看不慣下去的事情
On the other hand, everyone thinks it should be good
從另外一方面看 各位覺得應該很好
There should be some enthusiastic people in this society
這個社會應該有一些很熱心的一些民眾
You should be very concerned about some social welfare matters
對於一些社會公益的事情應該要很關心
But from another perspective, he felt that there were so many accusations
可是他從另外一方面講 就覺得說怎麼那麼多檢舉
Why so many cups
怎麼那麼多料杯
why so many of these things
怎麼那麼多這些事情
What about this matter?
那這件事情的話呢 其實
From another point of view?
從另外一方面來看的話呢
In fact, it should be worthy of our concern
其實也應該值得我們關心
How will our society and culture develop?
我們這個社會文化到底要怎麼發展
because if you cut in from the other side
因為如果你從另外一方面切入的話
The reason why I feel that I should share this matter with you
之所以會引起我覺得應該要跟大家分享這件事情的話呢
I think it will fundamentally shape the shake
我覺得它會根本的會來塑造動搖
each of us to the other
我們每個人對於其他人的一個那個分際
we feel very enthusiastic
我們覺得是很熱心
But from another perspective
可是從另外一方面來講的話
For example, in terms of traffic violations
如果是以譬如說以違規交通違規來講
What about traffic violations?
交通違規來講的話呢
Of course the capabilities of the police are limited.
當然警察的能力是有限的
So what he's saying now is certainly encouraging.
所以他現在目前的話當然很鼓勵
Everyone, if the public can take the initiative to report
大家如果民眾可以主動檢舉
Even if there are some
甚至的話呢還可以有些
You still have to share some benefits
你還要分到一些利益
Then everyone should also know
那大家另外也應該也很知道
Some people don't talk about survival because of this.
有人就以此不要講維生啦
At least as a side job.
起碼以此為副業也可以了
What about this situation, everyone?
那這情況的話呢各位
we continue to encourage
我們這樣繼續鼓勵
if you continue
繼續下去的話
trust between people
人與人之間的信任
between people
人與人之間的
What about this kind of interaction?
這種互動的話呢
Is it built on this whistle blowing culture?
是不是就建立在這種檢舉文化
whistleblower culture
這種檢舉文化
is it good or not
是好呢還是不好
This is something we should really think about
這個我們其實是值得我們好好去想的
Then he will talk today
那他今天他就講說
Actually, you can't do this well
其實這件事情你做不好
When you want the people to come out instead
你要反而要民眾出來的時候
Actually you should think about two things
其實你應該思考兩件事情
The first is the question of the capacity of the government
第一個是政府的能力的問題
you are becoming incompetent
你是變得無能
The second question to consider is that
那第二個要思考的問題是說
I don't even know whether the general public should be allowed to
根本知道是不是應該要讓一般的民眾
know to abide by the law
知道要守法
minimum traffic rules
最起碼的交通規則
or a bare minimum
或者是一個最起碼的東西
As a result, we don't use this to come today
結果今天我們不用這個來
Instead, through what?
反而是要透過什麼呢
by reporting
透過檢舉的方式
and then through punishment
然後透過處罰的方式
then to strengthen
然後來加強
It's you who violated me today
就是你今天入我違反
anytime anywhere
隨時隨地
sorry
對不起喔
you anytime, anywhere
你隨時隨地的話
you pay attention to what's around you
你注意你周遭的
i obviously mean
我明顯是說
Be careful, the spies are by your side
小心匪諜就在你身邊
change today
今天換
Be careful and resolute is by your side
要注意到小心堅決就在你身邊
In that case, actually
那這樣子的話其實
On the other hand
另外一方面的話
Wait a minute, I'll tell you about it at the beginning
等一下就要跟開始跟各位講到是說
this will follow
這個會跟
Some developments in the kind of privacy that we are talking about today
我們今天談的隱私隱私的那種隱私權的一些發展
It is related to some developments in the information society
跟資訊社會的一些發展會有關係
Let's leave a little foreshadowing first
我們先留下一點伏筆
that is
就是
such a culture
這樣子的一個文化
In fact, he will speak slowly
其實他也會慢慢說到出
human interaction
人與人之間的互動
What kind of relationship would result in
到底會產生什麼樣子的一個關係的一種
or what one looks like
或者是什麼樣子的一個
interactive relationship
互動的關係
Then this situation
那這個情況
It may be that we will spend a little more time and come back to talk to you
可能是等一下我們再花一點時間再過來跟各位講
Let me take a moment now to tell you what the right to privacy is
我現在花一點時間來跟各位講什麼是隱私權
Maybe the word here might become a comparison
也許這邊的話呢可能會變成比較
not very interesting
不是很很有趣啦
Because he was entered into the legal challenge
因為他就被進入到法律挑文了
privacy is important
隱私很重要
Privacy is what we just talked about
隱私就是我們剛剛講到了
Maybe something I don't want others to know
也許是一些我不想讓別人知道的一些
personal facts
個人的實事
or the one i should
或者是一個我應該
let me have a space alone
讓我有獨處的一個空間
Have privacy and space
有私務跟空間
but if today
但是如果今天的話
don't have a stake
沒有一個權益
no legal right
沒有一個法律的權
If the legal system guarantees
如果法律制度來保障的話
maybe this privacy
可能這個隱私
it will be violated
它就會受到侵害
so privacy
所以隱私權的話
designed words
設計出來的話
Mainly to protect personal privacy
主要就是要來保障個人的隱私
but
但是
what we want to tell you
我們要跟各位是說的話
Privacy words in the modern sense of privacy
在隱私現代意義的隱私權的話
In fact, at the end of the 19th century
其實是在19世紀末期
just started like this
才開始有這樣子的
modern concept of privacy
現代的隱私權的觀念
That
那
earliest now present words
最早現在目前的話
in academia
在學界裡面
At least in academia
最少在學界裡面的話
When it comes to modern privacy
一談到近代隱私權的
the establishment of a system
一個制度的建立的話
was started in 1890
是開始在1890年
words from 1890
1890年的話
these two lawyers
這兩位律師
professional lawyer at the time
當時的職業律師
Both work in Boston
都是在波斯頓職業
This Samuel Warren
這個 Samuel Warren
Louis Brandeis
跟Louis Brandeis
what they wrote
他們所寫的
Then this article is published in Hoverloo Review
然後這篇文章的話是登在Hoverloo Review
what is the topic of their writing
他們寫的題目是什麼
The title they wrote was The Right to Privacy
他們寫的題目是The Right to Privacy
The Right to Privacy
The Right to Privacy
Then from 1890 onwards
那從1890年開始之後的話
The words of this article gradually become a repeatedly quoted
這一篇文章的話就逐漸變成一個反覆被引用的
Then everyone is talking about film and television rights
然後每個人在談影視 影視權的話
will come back to them in the end
最後就會回到他們
Of course, everyone can understand, if they should.
那當然大家可以如果應該也可以理解吧
The formation of a concept is never attributable to
一個概念的形成絕對不是歸住於
Home to these two today
今天就歸住這兩個人
There must be a gestation period
一定是有一段醞釀的期
Then just this paragraph
然後剛好這段
The words of the two of them caught one eye.
這個他們兩個人的話就抓住了一眼
then it came out
然後就出來了
So anyway
所以不過不管怎麼說的話
let's talk about this article
我們就講這篇文章
That
那
Brandeis is a very important
Brandeis是一個非常重要的
what about these two
那這兩位的話
That was at Hoverloo School
那當時是在Hoverloo School的話
If you read books, you are bedmates
讀書的話是同床朋友
First place Second place
第一名 第二名
then work at the same time
然後同時職業
he is very rich
那他非常有錢
he is jewish
那他是猶太人
What about Brandice, who later became very famous
那Brandice的話呢後來非常有名的
It's not just this article
實在於不是光是這篇文章
It's that he later became a justice of the United States Supreme Court.
而是他後來變成美國最高法院的法官
justice
大法官
become very important
變成非常重要的人物
right to privacy
他除了對隱私權
we'll talk beyond him
我們會談到他之外
The words in Free Speech Studies will also talk about him
在言論自由的研究的話也會談到他
Then we have to pay attention to the social background at that time
那我們要注意到這個當時的社會背景
sorry
對不起
I have a bad throat recently
我最近喉嚨比較不好
I'm worried that there will be no sound after a while
我很擔心等一下就沒有聲音了
Everyone noticed that he was a
大家注意到就是當時他是一個
From an agricultural society to an industrial society
從農業社會變成工業社會
what is he doing
他在做什麼呢
Then he is an immigrant society
然後呢他是一個移民的社會
Everyone, think about your childhood
各位在想想看小時候
or as a child
或小時候
Do you all use the same childhood as us?
各位是不是用跟我們一樣同樣的小時候
When I was a child, I grew up as the head of the dependent village
小時候是眷村長長大
I don't know if you guys are from the general
我不曉得大家各位是不是來自於一般的
Compare
比較
Compare relatives and friends together
比較親朋好友同在一起的
The so-called rural society
這種所謂的鄉村社會
What about that kind of society?
那種社會的話呢
What about him because of emotions
他呢因為情緒
Everyone, what happened to my house?
大家其實我家發生什麼事情
compare soon
比較很快就知道
Of course, the partition wall is also poor in sound insulation.
隔牆當然隔音設備也很差
On the other hand, of course
當然另外一方面來講
Interacting with each other is also very weak
彼此往來也非常弱弱
different from now
跟現在不一樣
you can think about it
大家可以想想看
a society like that
那時候那樣子的一個社會
In a village where I live
在一個我居住在一個鄉村裡面
or live in a town
或居住在一個城鎮裡面
or live in a place
或居住在一個地方
If something happens to my house
結果我家發生什麼事情的話
everyone around knows
周遭的人都知道
Then what kind of Privacy is there at that time?
那請問那時候還有什麼Privacy
At that time Privacy may
那時候Privacy可能
No
沒有
when will he
什麼時候他會
Becoming a Privacy may be the conclusion of living with strangers
變成Privacy 可能就是生存在陌生的人的總結
What about this era?
那這個時代的話呢
he might be like this for a reason
他可能會有這樣子的原因
They come out like this because of industrialization
他們會有這樣出來是因為工業化了
It's all melted
都是化了
what about your thoughtful person
你周到的人的話呢
what is no more
不再多是什麼呢
Your former uncle
你以前的叔叔伯伯啦
or auntie
或者是阿姨啦
or these relatives and friends
或者是這些親朋好友
We've been used to it since childhood
從小到大我們都很習慣的
He should know what happened in my house
我家發生什麼事情他應該都知道
So we're now at a
那我們現在到了一個
is an unfamiliar environment
是一個陌生的環境
strangers around
陌生的周遭的一些陌生人
So what about the words between strangers?
所以陌生人中間彼此之間的話呢
don't have that kind of trust
沒有那種信任
what happened to me
那我發生什麼事情呢
he talks casually
他隨便講一講
misunderstood by others
就別人就誤以為
But what if today
可是如果今天的話呢
I'm like the village I grew up in
是我像我從小長大的鄉村的
A place like this is all about me
這樣子的一個周遭的全部都是我
people who know me
都認識我的人
what happened to me
我發生什麼事情
at least they won't misread me
他們起碼不會誤讀我
So I'm going to say one thing here
所以我這邊講一個就是說
Someone will talk about what diet is
有人會談什麼叫做飲食
Why should the right to food be protected?
為什麼要保障飲食權的話呢
Someone cut in from this angle
有人就從這個角度切進去
cut it in
切進去就是
that is
就是說
because of it
因為的話呢
Afraid that others will misinterpret it
怕別人他會錯誤的解讀
you get these messages
你得到這些訊息
Then your message isn't enough
接著你的訊息其實是不夠的
On the other hand
另外一方面的話
You told him other than this message
你對他除了這個訊息之外
do you know anything else about him
你對他其他東西了解嗎
You do not get it
你不了解
As a result, you interpret it like this
結果你就把它解讀出來是這樣
so he is also afraid
所以他也怕
So some people think that
所以有人就認為是說
Fear of being misunderstood by others
怕別人有錯誤的解讀
so someone said
所以有人就說
This is an alternative view on protecting the right to privacy
這是一個保障隱私權的另而有觀點
But that point of view is relatively
不過那個觀點是比較
It was only proposed after modern times
現代後面才提出來的
in the middle of communication
在傳在通訊中間
no one talks about this
比較沒有人談這一塊
But I think he is worth it
不過我是覺得他是值得大家可以
By the way, I can share with you
順便可以跟各位分享一下
what is the second one
那第二個是什麼呢
The second is technology
第二個是科技
The technology at that time was called photography
那時候的科技叫照相技術
Now what are you guys talking about?
現在各位來講算什麼
But back then the technology of photography was amazing
不過那時候的科技照相技術很了不起
because it was from that time
因為當時是從那個
need your tripod
需要你三腳架的
then hit that
然後打那個的
and then what
然後變成什麼的
He can take it with him
他隨身可以帶的 攜帶的
But at that time, the light bulb was
不過那時候隨身攜帶的話那個燈泡是
Throw away when you're done, Throw away when you're done
造完就要丟掉 造完就要丟掉的
But anyway, he was a breakthrough
可是不管怎麼樣的話 他是一個突破
That is, he is very convenient. He is a portable
就是他很便捷 他是一個隨身可以
moodable he is a mobile
moodable 他是一個mobile的
So what if this is the case, everyone?
所以這樣情況之下的話呢 各位
The front Warran between the two
這兩個人中間的前面那個Warran
He just him because his family is very rich
他就 他 因為他家是很有錢的人
What about his wife?
那他的太太的話呢
I also told the wife of the president at the time
也跟當時的總統的夫人的話
It's also a boudoir
也算是密閨
Still a bestie, should be a bestie
還是閨密 應該是閨密
not boudoir
不是密閨
They're supposed to be best friends, so they're actually one.
應該是閨密 所以他們其實是一個
In terms of politics, everyone is satisfied
在政治上來講的話 大家也還滿
I think it's number one
覺得是算是一號人物
So what happened to his house?
所以他家發生什麼事情的話呢
The newspapers at that time published every episode
當時的報紙的話 每集都登了
So actually I should tell you one more thing
所以其實我還應該跟各位再多講一個
New technologies other than these three
除了這三個之外的新技
Information Technology In addition to this modeling technology
資訊科技 除了這個造型技術之外
Another new technology is newspapers
還有一個新的技術 就是報紙
Newspapers at the time
報紙 當時的報紙
I ignored it here
我這邊忽略掉了
newspapers at the time
當時的報紙
So that newspaper at that time from the 19th century
所以那個報紙在那個時候從19世紀
start slowly
出啟 慢慢慢慢
If it develops to that time, he will start to come out halfway.
發展到那時候的話 他半半開始出來了
At that time, of course newspapers also competed with each other.
那時候的話 報紙當然也互相的競爭
he needs this too
他也需要用這個
these businesses
這些商業
these advertisements to maintain his operations
這些這些廣告來維持他的這些營運
i think these words i'm not saying
我想這些的話 我不是說
use him to speak now
用他來講現在
Think about it, when did he cause
大家想想看 什麼時候他引起了
Proposing such a concept
這樣子一種概念的提出
What is said today, what is said in our current society
那今天的話 在我們現在社會的話
In fact, he made some transformations. In the middle of this transformation,
其實他又做了一些轉變 在這種轉變中間的話
In fact, he should change those concepts a bit.
那些概念其實他也應該要有點轉變
Well, I'm just here to tell you about this matter.
那我這邊只是跟各位講這件事情
so we're going to mention this
所以我們要提這個這個
other than this thing
除了這個東西之外的話
I write a lot of things that don't need to be said
我寫很多東西不需要講
I'm just talking to you guys
我只是跟各位講說
Why do they bring these things up
他們為什麼會提出這些東西出來
then speak to them
然後對他們來講的話
words in their most original sense
他們最原始的意義的話
They think it means don't get fucked
他們認為就是說 不要受點乾
just don't come and leave me alone
就不要來不要管我
leave me alone
不要管我就好了
That
那
After starting here
這邊開始之後
after starting here
這邊開始之後的話
They were proposed in 1890
他們是1890年提出來
Afterwards, these things in the United States at that time
之後的話 當時的美國的這些
judicial
司法
or the word of congress
或者是國會的話
not too serious
還沒有太認真
By 1901, there was even a case in the state of New York
到了1901年的時候 甚至紐約州的話 有一個案子
In that case, a flour mill used a
那個案子的話 就是一個麵粉工廠的話 用了一個
Woman taking his picture as his without the woman's consent
婦人 沒有經過那個婦人同意的話 就把他的照片當作他的
advertise
廣告
put it on the flour sack
放到麵粉袋上
Then what this woman said, I feel like talking about him
那這個婦人的話 就覺得說他的
His privacy was violated, sue this New York state
他的隱私受害侵害 那就告了這個紐約州的
The state courts did not win the state courts, I think
州的法院 結果沒有贏州法院 我認為說
This is an invasion of his privacy
這是侵害他隱私
what about when you come out
那當你出來之後的話呢
Many residents of the New York state who died felt that what to say
對死的那紐約州的很多居民的話 就覺得說怎麼
It's okay to do such a thing, but you're not a New York state citizen.
可以這樣的事情 其實不是紐約州州民
Actually the New York Times
其實是紐約時報
This is why the newspapers at that time were very important. The newspapers talked about it from the very beginning
這樣子講 所以當時的報紙很重要 報紙一開始就講怎麼
Can it be like this? After this, it will cause everyone
可以這樣子呢 這樣子之後的話呢 就引起大家
In the field of linguistics, in the field of intellectuals, in the field of social management
語論界的 還有知識界的社會上的經營的話
take things like this very seriously
就非常重視這樣的事情
So, the New York State Congress will pass legislation
所以呢 紐約州的國會的話呢 他就通過立法
So his earliest legislation
所以他最早的立法
He puts a privacy right like this
他就把這樣子的一個隱私權
the privacy they want to assert
他們想主張的隱私權的話
the way he passed the legislation
他就把他後過立法的方式
into their torts
放入到他們的侵權行為裡面去
Then the development will be very fast
那後來的發展就很快了
words developed later
後來發展的話
Every state is different
每一個州情況就不一樣
words in some states
有些州的話
He speaks straight to the court
他直接就透法院的話
Just use the way of Conmannuo directly
就直接用康芒諾的方式
Because of Facomano's way
因為法康芒諾的方式
directly into a judgment precedent
直接就變成一個判決先例
other states
另外有些州的話
He made it a state law
他就變成州法放進去
Then in 1960
那到1960年的時候
in 1960
1960年的時候
this
這個
Burkeley Low School's then
Burkeley Low School的當時的
The dean of Burkeley Low School in the United States
美國Burkeley Low School的那個院長
CalledWilliam Prosser
叫William Prosser
Words from William Prosser
William Prosser的話
he put this
他就把這個
from 1960
從1960年
Between 1890 and 1960
1890年到1960年這中間的
The court ruled that he should consult with him
法院的判決他就把他會診
after the consultation
會診完之後的話
He just said what our American society says
他就說我們美國社會的話
For words like invasion of privacy
對於像侵害隱私權這種的話
The four types of privacy violations
這個四種侵害隱私權類型
he summed him up
他就把他歸納出來
Then let me just say it here.
那我這邊的話順便就講
This Warren proposed to Brandeis
這個瓦仁跟布蘭黛斯他們提出
When the right to privacy
那個the right to privacy的時候
he is not created out of nothing
他也不是無中生有
what is he actually
他其實也是什麼呢
he also said
他也是說
I take all past court decisions
我把過去所有法院的判決
related to these
跟這些有關
I think what I'm trying to bring up
我認為跟我所要提出來的
the right to privacy
the right to privacy
about these judgments
有關的這些判決
he also found him
他也把他找出來
He is through the experience of being
他是透過存在的經驗
then he put him
然後他把他
Analysis after kneeling
跪整完之後分析
and then sum it up
然後歸納出來說
others did not see he saw
別人沒看到他看到
That 1960's
那1960年的這個
What about Professor Proser?
Proser教授的話呢
He did the same
他也做了同樣的情況
same way
同樣的一種方法
also used the past
也用了過去
That is, from 1890 to 1960
就是從1890年到1960年
Judgment of the Intermediate Court
中間法院的判決
he summed him up
他把他歸納出來
So they basically say
所以他們基本上都說
not they created
不是他們創建
they just take what has happened
他們只是把已經發生的事情
he summed him up
他把他歸納出來
so relatively
所以相對
So what about the words?
所以來講的話呢
The creation of your academics is sometimes quite difficult to talk about
你創建學者的創建有些時候還蠻難去講的
this is your unfamiliarity
這是你疏生之見
if he already exists
如果他是已經存在的
so that others do not see
讓別人沒有看到的
I point you out
我把你點出來說
In fact, he already exists there
其實他已經存在在那一邊了
He's actually quite easy to move around.
他其實事實上是比較容易大動的
So they came up with these
所以他們後來提出來的這些
This type of infringement of film and television rights
這種侵害影視權的類型
or infringement of the type of infringement of film and television rights
或侵權行為的侵害影視權類型的話
In fact, it has affected the development of related infringements in the world.
其實就影響了世界有關侵權行為的發展
Taiwan is particularly affected by this
台灣尤其受到這方面的影響
What about the impact here?
那這邊的影響的話呢
Of course mainly because
當然主要是因為
In addition to the previous piece we just talked about
除了我們剛才談到的前面那一塊
That piece is talking
那一塊中間在談
From the right of secrets to the right of film and television
從這個從秘密權變成影視權
at the turning point in the middle
那個中間的轉折的時候
A lot of discussions there are actually talking about this thing.
那裡面很多的討論其實就在談這個東西
will talk about you can watch when
就會談說你可以看那時候
America they have developed
美國他們有發展出來
A so-called infringement of film and television rights
一個所謂侵害影視權的這種侵權行為
So that's what they're talking about
所以他們在談的就在談那一塊
What about Germany's weakness?
那德國這一個敗弱的話呢
they are talking
他們也是在談
Infringement
侵權行為
Tell them the right to secrecy
為他們講秘密權
Later words slowly developed to the present words come in
後來的話慢慢發展到現在的話進來
To come in is to officially become
進來的話是正式的成為
But everyone should know that this is officially becoming
不過各位要知道就是說這個正式成為
from Taiwan
我們台灣的
law
法律
then it becomes
然後變成是說
It's us
是我們
If someone violates my privacy, I can claim
如果有人侵害我隱私的話呢我可以來主張
What about infringement
侵權行為的話呢
is going to
是要到
we are at
我們在
Although we are talking about the revision of the civil law very early, we have been talking about it since the Republic of China in 1970
雖然我們在談民法修正很早吧民國1970年開始就在談
Civil Law Amendment
民法修正
But the real civil law amendment
但是真正民法修正
is going to
是要到
Only implemented in 1990
1990年才真正實施
That is in our general principles of civil law
那個是在我們的民法總則
195 he corrected it
195條他把它修正
so
所以
It's funny here, at least when I was a student
這邊很有趣我起碼我當學生的時候
when i was a student
我當學生的時候呢
There are many cases of well-known cases
有很多案件很有名的案件
Some say it's a violation of privacy
有人就說這是侵害隱私權
So it should be an invasion of privacy
所以應該是侵害隱私
but sorry
但是很對不起的
Because it's an invasion of privacy, you should go and read the Civil Code.
因為這是侵害隱私 那你去看看民法法條
Inside, Article 195 talks about invasion of privacy
裡面的話呢195條在講侵害隱私的
infringe on this
侵害這種
If you can ask for the right to be spiritually majestic
精神上可以請求精神上威風精的這種權利的話
does not include privacy
並沒有包括隱私在裡面
he has reputation health body reputation health these
他有名譽健康身體名譽健康這些
However, it does not include the so-called
可是並沒有包括所謂的
privacy
隱私
so sorry
所以對不起
he can't ask
他不能夠請求
Compensation for damage
所害賠償
At that time, apart from the privacy controversy, another
當時除了隱私這個爭議之外另外一個
called a quarrel
叫做爭吵
At that time, there were many such sexual assault cases in Taiwanese society.
當時台灣社會有發生很多這種性侵害案件
What to do if you are assaulted in a sexual assault case
性侵害案件的話你侵害的話怎麼辦
So at that time, the words used to violate the body
所以當時的話就用侵害身體
come here with your body
用身體那邊過來
What about privacy?
那有關隱私這塊怎麼辦呢
words of some courts
有些法院的話
They accept the honor
他們就接受用名譽過來
Came here with damage to his reputation because he couldn't find anyone who could use his privacy to claim damages
用侵害名譽過來 因為他找不到可以請用隱私來請求所害賠償的
So let me tell you by the way
所以我順便跟各位講
Then this is coming officially
那這個要正式要到
After the civil law was amended we have
民法修正之後我們才有
What about other than this film and television rights?
那除了這個影視權除了這之外的話呢
if we look
如果我們來看的話
is later continued to develop
是後來又繼續發展
These four types of infringement of film and television rights may wait a minute, maybe I will follow along and talk to you about that.
這個四種侵害影視權類型等一下也許就順著等一下可以跟各位談那個
Development of Information Technology
資訊科技的發展
By the way, I'll talk to you guys again
順便再跟各位談
The development of film and television rights, in addition to infringement
那影視權的發展除了侵權行為之外
It's civil, it's between us private and private
那是民事間的就是我們私人跟私人之間的
if we are here
如果我們在這個
between private and private if my
私人跟私人之間的如果我的
If my video is infringed on by others, I can come and request
我的影視受到其他私人侵害的話我可以來請求
This damage is very
這個損害非常
On the other hand, you can understand that
那另外一方面的話呢各位可以理解到是說
If he is that important, is there any criminal case other than private through civil
如果他是那麼重要的話除了私人私人之間透過民事之外有沒有刑事的
In the middle of a criminal case, we can also later
刑事案件中間的話後來我們也可以
Seeing that there is crime of harm prevention secret
看到有防害秘密罪
The most typical one is
那個最典型的就是
Because real hole photography has come out
因為真孔攝影已經出來了
Words to prevent pore photography after it has come out
防止真孔攝影已經出來之後的話
cause a lot of things like this
造成非常多的類似這種
I was in a private space
本來我在一個私密空間
I don't want others to know
我不想讓別人知道
It turns out that you used this porosity camera to invade
結果你用這種真孔攝影機來侵害到
so soon after
所以後來很快
Once it is revised in the criminal law, it will be over soon.
那個在刑法裡面一修這很快就過了
Because the social groups at that time felt that
因為當時社會群體感覺得到
how can it be like this
怎麼可以這個樣子
So we have both civil law and criminal law
所以我們在民法刑法都有
What about later?
那後來的話呢
Actually faster
其實比較更快的
In addition to civil law and criminal law
除了民法跟刑法之外
It is faster development in Taiwan
就是更快在臺灣的發展
He is upside down with America
他跟美國是倒過來的
It's the other way around with Europe
跟歐洲也倒過來的
It is because our administrative regulations existed earlier
是我們行政法規比較早就有
In the words of our administrative regulations
在我們行政法規的話
at least since 1988
起碼在1988年
or before 1989
或1989年之前
We should have some regulations
我們應該就有存在有些法規的話呢
he will come
他就會來
it will be regulated
裡面就會規範
You can't invade someone's special identity
你不能夠去侵含到一些人的特殊身份的人
human his privacy
人的 他的隱私
So we can see several conditions
所以我們可以看到幾個條件
A few words from this section on privacy protection
幾個 這個有關隱私權保障的部分的話
The first thing we saw was to start from the act of clearing up rights in civil law
我們最早看到是從民法清權行為切進
Then, if this is the case, if it is the development of the United States
然後後來如果這樣 如果是美國那邊的發展的話
He later arrived in the 1960s
他後來到了1960年代
started another wave
開始了另外一波的
Except we just talked about the 1960s
除了我們剛才談到1960年代
Professor Proser's words, he summed up the behavior of clearing power
Proser教授的話 他把歸納出那種清權行為之外
Note also that in the 1960s and 1970s
當時還要注意到 六零年代到七零年代
In the middle, the computerization at that time
中間的話 當時的computerization 電腦化
he also showed up
他也出現了
So when computerization comes
所以電腦化出現的時候
make American society, those they start to worry about
使得美國社會 那些他們就開始擔心
Personal information, will it be the result of computerization?
個人的資料的話 會不會因為電腦化的結果的話
he was violated
他受到侵害
So they started another wave a new one
所以他們開始了另外一波新的一個
A direction to protect the right to privacy through legislation
透過立法的方式來保障隱私權的一個區向
Then this area is actually in the United States and Europe
那這個區向其實是在美國跟歐洲
Maybe they were more advanced then
他們也許當時的話是比較先進
So it's weird what I was talking about
所以我剛才在講很奇怪
Why after the 1970s
為什麼到1970年代之後
The word our photographer is positioned
我們的那個影師這個字就定位了
Is that what the world cared about at the time?
那是不是也跟世界當時在關心
new cinematographer concept
新的影師的觀念
When a new photographer invades
新的影師侵害的時候
some fads are related
一些風潮是有關係的
Since the late 1960s and into the 1970s
因為1960年代末期開始到1970年代
The most discussed part in the middle is about the computerization of personal data
中間的話討論最多的就是有關個人資料的電腦化
If personal data is computerized
個人資料電腦化的話
They found out that the words
他們就發現到說這種情況的話
Simply through civil tort is not enough
單單純純的透過民事侵權行為是不足的
because what is that
因為那個是什麼
between private and private
是私人跟私人之間
Today is the country to invade me
今天是國家來侵害我
computerization of the country
國家透過電腦化
Then he came to collect a lot of statistics
然後他來收集大量的統計資料
Census Statistics
人口普查統計資料
How can these things be replaced?
那這些東西的話怎麼讓代
So they started to legislate
所以他們就開始透過立法的方式
to do this
來做這件事情
Of course, the most famous and typical one is the protection of personal data.
那裡面當然最有名的最典型的就是有關個人資料的保護
So after the 70s words
所以在70年代之後的話
new wave
新的一波
In addition to infringement, another wave of words
除了侵權行為之外 另外一波的話
It's Personal Therapy Protection, and it's been around since then.
就是個人治療保護 就從那時候開始
just like that
就這樣推進來了
That
那
What about Taiwan?
台灣呢
Taiwan
台灣
Our development just reversed
我們的發展剛好倒過來
if pure if pure
如果單純的 如果單純的
From that legal title
從那個法律名文規定
In this way, our privacy protection
這樣子來說我們的隱私權保障的話
we may be upside down
我們可能是倒過來
We are first prescribed by law
我們是先由法律規定
Some provisions of administrative law
行政法一些規定的話
like i just talked about
像我剛才談到的
words from 1989
1989年的話
Possibly in banking law
可能是在銀行法裡面
words in banking law
銀行法裡面的話
for bank customers
對於銀行的客戶的
His personal financial information
他的個人的那些財務資料的話
should be maintained
應該要維護
that privacy
那個隱私權
What if we come again?
再過來的話呢
is typical
很典型的就是
Computer Processing Personal Therapy Protection Act
電腦處理個人治療保護法
Words of the Computerized Personal Therapy Protection Act
電腦處理個人治療保護法的話
before what
先於什麼呢
amendments prior to civil law
先於民法的修正
What about the reason?
那這個原因的話呢
There may be other reasons behind
可能背後有其他的原因
Computer Processing Personal Therapy Protection Act
電腦處理個人治療保護法
The reason why I asked quickly was because
當時問很快的原因是因為
At that time, Taiwan hoped to become an Asia-Pacific operation
台灣當時是希望變成亞太營運
Operations Center
營運中心
In order to become the Asia-Pacific operations center
那為了要變成亞太營運中心的話
to know that means I need to accept
那就要知道是說我需要接受
If we wish to put
如果我們希望把
Other companies that have become multinational
其他變成跨國的公司
Ability to set up in Taiwan
能夠在台灣設置
set up his Asia-Pacific
設立他在亞太的
If the head office is located in Taiwan
總公司是設在台灣的話
then these companies
那麼這些公司
A profile at some other company should be able to
在其他某公司的資料就應該能夠
Find a way to come to Taiwan
想辦法到台灣來
Taiwan also has to find a way
台灣也要想辦法
Relevant transaction information should also be found out
有關的交易資料也要想辦法出去
if you're going to be like this
如果你要變成這樣子的話
but noticed
可是注意到
what we're talking about is saying
我們說到的是說
Because of personal data protection this started
因為個人資料保護這個開始了
that in Europe at the time
那在當時的歐洲
European Community
歐洲共同經濟體
economic community
經濟共同體
predecessor of the european union
歐盟的前身
words of the predecessor of the european union
歐盟歐盟的前身的話
They also had a word about this matter very early
他們很早也對這件事情的話
they also care
他們也很關心
So they've made a spec
所以他們已經做了一個規範
This specification is
這個規範就是
There are regulations on so-called safe harbors
有關於所謂安全港的規範
It's today
就是今天
with these countries in the European Union
跟我歐盟的這些國家
sorry eu
對不起歐盟
that was the european union
那是當時的歐盟
that economy
那個經濟體
We will then
我們就
Since everyone in the European Union is better than him
歐盟既然大家比他熟了
Just say it is the European Union
嘴巴就出來就是歐盟
If you want to share the economy with me
如果你要跟我這個共同經濟體
economic community
經濟共同體
If you want to be an official and do these business dealings
要做官做這些商務往來的話
It specifically mentioned what this is
那中間特別講到這是一個什麼
My information is from
我的資訊要從
countries of the european community
歐洲共同體的這些國家
to another country
到另外一個國家的話
this kind
這種
Information flow across borders
跨國境的資訊流通
He has one request
他有一個要求就是
To stay in that country, that country must have the same norms
要留到那個國家的話那個國家必須要有相同的規範
Protection of personal data
保障個人資料
Otherwise, my information will pass
否則的話我資料就過去
Therefore, everyone is very clear about this situation. If Taiwan wants to become this
所以這種情況大家就很清楚如果你臺灣要想成為這
Words from the Asia-Pacific Immigration Center
亞太的移民中心的話
then what becomes
那就變成什麼呢
I also have to have the same specification
我也必須要相同的規範
So when we
所以我們那時候呢
This computer processing personal data protection law will pass soon
這個電腦處理個人資料保護法很快就過了
In fact, if what we are doing is advanced in the legal field, everyone can understand
其實如果我們在做的有法律界的先進的話大家可以理解
In fact, there were actually a lot of discussions at that time, and other proposals were quickly passed.
其實當時其實討論非常多其他的議法就很快就先過
So we went through the computer first
所以我們先過了電腦處理
The Personal Data Protection Act and then come back to have amendments to the civil law
個人資料保護法 然後再過來才有民法的修正
and then put this tort part
然後才把這個民事侵權行為的部分
With film and television rights
有加上影視權
So our development
所以我們的發展
no the same
不一樣
But now the word is through these
不過現在目前的話也就是透過這些
But there's another, more important part, a more important one
但是另外更重要的一個部分 更重要的一個
partly
部分是
Is he a de jure right after all we talked about
他到底是不是一個卸法上的權利 我們剛才談到的
what is
是什麼
he's a civil tort he's a legal tort
他是一個民法侵權行為 他是一個法律上的權益
he is personal computer personal data processing personal data protection law
他是個人電腦 個人資料 處理個人資料保護法
If the protection of personal data in that personal data
如果那個個人資料裡面的保護個人資料的話
If there is also protection of film and television rights, what is he?
也有保護影視權的話 他也是一個什麼呢
He is also a legal interest
他也是一個法律上的權益
So is he a constitutional right?
那他到底是不是一個憲法上的權益
If he goes over the Constitution of the Republic of China
他如果去翻中華民國憲法
in our constitution
我們憲法中間
no mention of video rights
並沒有提到影視權
So what about film rights?
所以影視權呢
If you want to realize it well, you can't control it well
有求實現好 沒有控制好
Before the unification of the information society, the time is approaching
還沒統一資訊社會就快到時間
So I'm going to enter the information society soon
所以我很快要進入資訊社會
If our justice is the part of the constitution that protects the right to privacy
我們大法官是憲法這個保障隱私權這個部分的話
through the justice's explanation
是透過大法官的解釋
So now in our Taiwan
所以現在目前在我們台灣的話
privacy
隱私權
the right to privacy it's also a power in the constitution
隱私權它也是憲法中的一種權力
we can't jump
我們就跳不去了
We Christian Information Society
我們基督資訊社會
Everyone in the information society think about a question
資訊社會各位想想看一個問題
Everyone use mobile phones
大家都用手機吧
right
對不對
Is there anyone without a cell phone?
有人不用手機的嗎
have all
都有嘛
Everyone uses a mobile phone, so you can understand why you use a mobile phone
大家都用手機那你各位可以理解手機為什麼要用手機呢
Mobile phones have become an indispensable part of our daily life.
手機對我們來講的話已經變成日常生活中間不可少
very convenient, isn't it
非常方便 對不對
I take out my phone when I do something
我做什麼事情的話就把手機拿出來
Maybe there are many people now
說不定現在目前的話有很多人
Not looking at me, but looking at me through the phone
不是在看我 而是透過手機在看我
If this happens, there are many of you, right?
那這種現象的話呢 大家很多嘛 對不對
As we said before, many people are obsessed with mobile phones
我們以前在講說 很多人就迷手機
To what extent are you lost in your phone? Between each other
迷手機到一個什麼程度 彼此之間
If you are in the middle of the same crime, if you are chatting with each other
在同一個犯罪中間的話 彼此在聊天的話
Not talking, but through the phone
不是在對話 而是透過手機
this is very common
這是很平常的現象
that statement or phenomenon
那這種說法或這種現象
It's just describing why the phone it becomes
它只是在描述之所以 手機它變成
Indispensable in daily life
自我日常生活中間不可 缺少的東西
But the reason why we become indispensable
但是 之所以變成我們不可缺少的東西
It's because it provides us with too many convenient services, right?
是因為它提供我們太多便利的服務 對不對
Where am I going today I can't find
今天我要到哪邊去 我找不到
Where is our original branch, I always Google Map
我們原分所在哪邊 那我一向Google Map
Or map, it just points out Habang
或者Map 它就哈邦就指點
If it wins, I just follow it and get there, right?
它就贏著我就跟著它走 就到了 對不對
That's convenient, but the same
那很方便 但是同樣的
I want to enjoy such a service actually
我要享受這樣子的服務 其實
I have to give my information out
我必須要把我的資訊提供出去
come in exchange
來作為交換
when i'm going to
當我要到
when I use Google Maps
我要用Google Maps的時候
What will I definitely use?
我一定會用到什麼呢?
you must provide say
你一定要提供說
where am i now
我現在在哪裡?
So this kind of location
所以這種location的
Information about personal location
個人的location的那種資訊的話
you have to swap out
你就必須交換出去了
the same thing too much
這同樣東西太多了
So today's current words
所以今天目前的話
I'm here to ask you
我就來請問各位
Everyone, do you know
各位你知不知道
If you are using your mobile phone
在用手機的話
There is so much information exchanged
有交換那麼多的資訊
words of information
這些資訊的話
not just us
不只是我們這樣子
And it's anything we just need to surf the Internet on our mobile phone
而且是任何我們只要透過手機上網
That's basically information on mobile phones
那基本上就是在手機資訊
Then on the other hand
然後另外一方面的話
everyone starts today
各位今天開始
often tell you
常常就會跟你講說
words on your phone
你的手機的話
need to be updated
需要更新
The apps inside should also be updated
裡面的apps也要更新
Much
非常多
I update every day
我天天都在更新
how did he know about you
那他怎麼知道你的
What about updating?
要更新呢?
when i update my app
我在更新我的app的時候
Do you want to check out your other stuff by the way?
是不是順便看看你的別的東西?
so in many cases
所以在很多情況之下
when we use mobile phones
我們在用手機的時候
In fact, a lot of information has been exchanged
其實已經交換非常多的資訊
then i don't know guys
那我不曉得各位
what do you think about this
你怎麼想這件事情
I think this information is irrelevant
是認為說這個資訊沒有關係
It doesn't matter if he takes it
他拿走就無所謂
Maybe you all think that
那可能各位都認為是說
this has nothing to do with my privacy
這跟我隱私無關
nothing to do with my privacy
跟我隱私無關
It may also be that
也有可能是說呢
Although he has something to do with my privacy
他雖然跟我隱私有關
but you have a way
但是你有辦法
if not
如果不用的話
How to do it
怎麼辦呢
Then I will become an off-screen name
那我就變成畫外之名了
So in this case
所以這種情況之下的話
we are curious
我們就很好奇
In fact, many things today are like this
其實今天非常多的事情就是這樣子
we just talked about cell phone
我們剛才講手機
In fact, inside the National Taiwan University campus
其實台大校園裡面
We are looking inside the original
我們在看原本所裡面
I've seen several cameras
我已經看到好幾個攝影機了
then go out
那出去的話
probably a lot of cameras
大概也有很多的攝影機
To maintain campus safety
為了維護校園安全
There are also many cameras
也有很多的攝影機
In fact, any street
其實到了任何一個街道
You can see the camera when you enter privately
私自入口你就看到攝影機
then we take a taxi
然後我們坐計程車
taxi
計程車
Driving machine
行車機路器
Then wherever you go
然後走到哪邊的話都有
Everyone is watching us and we are watching others
每個人都在看我們 我們也在看別人
So now the current words
所以現在目前的話
probably into a
大概就進入到一種
Big Brother like 1984
像1984的那種老大哥
Watching you all the time, except for the government
隨時在看著你 可是除了政府的
What else is there besides this big brother?
這種老大哥之外 其實還有什麼呢
And these are our Rolomon
還有這些我們羅羅門
These little big brothers or little big sisters
這些小大哥或小大姐們
we are helping big brother
我們也在幫老大哥
So now society has become
所以現在目前社會就變成
enter into a
進入到一個
people are changing
全民都在變
Under surveillance, all the people are also there
被監視 全民也在
one who watches over others
監視別人的一個
This is monitoring
這種是監控
severance
severance
In this case, there is actually a risk
這個情況來講的話 它其實有一種風險
We just said that everyone is
我們剛才講到說 每個人都在
Report and report
檢舉檢舉
If any
如果任
we live in a so-called
我們生活在一個所謂的
In the era when all the people are being monitored
全民都被監控的時代的時候
Actually what does it mean here?
其實這裡面代表什麼意思
In fact, it is a discipline function
其實就是一個規訓的作用
we pass this way
我們透過這樣子
The most typical statement is
最典型的說法是
benson
Benson
This British philosopher Benton invented
這個英國哲學家Benton他發明出來
the so-called prototype prison theory
所謂的原型監獄理論
The words of his archetypal prison theory are
他原型監獄理論的話就是說
He can design this kind of prison called a prototype
他可以設計這種叫原型的監獄
He just needs to have a warden in the middle of this prison
他只要有一個管理員在這個監獄的中間
He can see inside every precaution
他可以看到每一個預防裡面
everyone is active
每個人都活動
Then don't those in the prevention
那別那個預防裡面的那些
the words of the prisoners
那些犯人的話
he can't see this admin
他看不到這個管理員
he can see them he can't see him
他可以看到他們 他看不到他
And what will he become in the last words?
然後最後的話他會變成什麼呢
None of this admin needs to exist
這個管理員都不需要存在
because of what
因為什麼呢
They don't know he can't see
他們根本不知道他看不
Are the admins watching them?
管理員有沒有在看他們
But he'll take it to mean they're looking at them
可是他都會認為是說他們在看著他們
just like today
就跟今天一樣
today's words
今天的話
I honestly don't know if anyone is watching me
老實說我也不知道有沒有人在看著我
But I know someone is watching me
可是我知道有人在看著我
That's an unknowable
那這就是一個不可知
What is the most troublesome thing today?
那今天最麻煩的一件事情就是什麼
The most troublesome thing is
最麻煩一件事情就是
we don't know
我們根本不知道
Information about who we are personally
我們的個人什麼樣子的資訊
by what kind of person
被什麼樣子的人
By what means does he collect
透過什麼樣的方法他收集
We don't know where he's stored
他儲存在哪邊 我們也不知道
Then how he was used we don't know
然後他怎麼被利用了 我們也不知道
We don't know what the result of his use is.
他利用的結果是怎麼樣 我們也不知道
this is now
這就是現在
To be honest, for me to do a research on shadow rights
老實說 對於我做一個要研究影子權的
To be honest, I have been talking to foreign scholars
老實說 我一直跟國外學者講說
I'm sorry, a lot of things are actually in my imagination
我很抱歉 很多東西其實我都是想像的
because we have no data
因為我們沒有資料
if you do research
如果你真要做研究的話
Of course you need to know what reality is
當然你就要知道現實是什麼嘛
You don't know reality, that's all you're imagining
你不知道現實都 那就是你全部都在憑空想像
but what is the reality
但是現實是什麼
reality is we don't know
現實是我們不知道
Our profile Says our profile on the Internet
我們個人資料 網路上說我們個人資料
I don't know if I'm used to it
是不是都被習慣了 我也不知道
Do you have our information over there? We don't know either.
你那邊有我們的資料嗎 我們也不知道
No matter how our data is used, we don’t know
就是我們資料再怎麼用 我們也不知道
Do not know at all
都不知道
In this case, it is irresistible to care
這種情況之下的話 就是在意不可辭
So today we will follow
所以我們在今天要跟
Sorry, I should have said this earlier today.
對不起 我今天其實這應該更早講
In fact, one important thing is
其實很重要一件事情就是
we have to understand
我們必須要理解
The exchange of social information today
今天這個社會資訊的交換
It is indispensable in our daily life
是我們這個日常生活中間不可少的
There's really no way around this
這個真的是沒有辦法少
but
但是
He should be a norm that must be justified
他應該是一個必須要被合理的規範
reasonable management
合理的管理
But we don't know what the mechanism is
可是我們不知道這個機制是什麼
Thanks
謝謝
So this is a question we want to talk to you today
所以這就是我們今天想跟各位談的一個問題
Well, we actually have some regulations in the law.
那我們其實法律裡面有一些規定
What about this law? For example, we just talked about the Personal Data Protection Law.
這個法律的話呢像譬如說我們剛剛講個人資料保護法
Or like some legal regulations just mentioned
或者是像剛剛談到一些法律規定的話
He actually had a hypothesis
他其實有個假設
because we just talked about privacy
因為我們剛剛談到隱私
In privacy, there is one thing he calls
隱私裡面的話呢有一件事情的話他叫做
I want to be in charge, I want to make my own decisions
我要當家做主我要自主決定
So, when protecting everyone's privacy through the law through the right to privacy of the law?
所以的話呢透過法律透過法律的隱私權來保障各位的隱私的時候呢
he has one thing
他有一件事情
It's very important, everyone may have heard it.
很重要大家也許都聽得到了聽過了就是
Hidden consent
隱封concent
be informed first
要先告知
Then with your consent
然後呢經過你同意
Then this becomes everything looks legal
那這個就變成一切看起來都合法
access to information
資訊的有取得
The collection, storage and utilization of this collection
這個收集的 收集儲存跟利用
is also true
也都是如此
If you have the consent of the parties
如果你經過當事人的同意
ok
ok
Then we'll look at the consent of the parties.
那我們就來看看當事人的同意
In fact, everyone
其實各位
We agree to so many things without knowing it
我們不知不覺就同意了非常多的事情
Yes or no
是不是
Like say you are using your phone today
像譬如說你今天在使用你的手機
use your computer use your many things
使用你的電腦 使用你很多的事情
He always asks if you agree or not
他都會問你嘛 同不同意
can you disagree
你能不同意嗎
if you disagree
你不同意的話
then it's gone
那就沒有了嘛
so it's an exchange
所以都是一種交換
One more troublesome thing is to say
更麻煩的一件事情是說
i have no idea what i'm agreeing to
我根本不知道我在同意什麼
Yes or no
是不是
Because he said so many terms
因為他講了那麼多的條款
Turns out we're more fun
結果我們更有趣 更
The contradictory thing is this
矛盾的事情是這樣子
that is
就是說
You can't protect consumers
你們不能夠為了要保護消費者
You can't speak so clearly
你們不能夠講那麼不清楚
As a result, he wanted to speak more clearly and longer
結果他為了要講更清楚 更長
then you don't even want to see
那你更不想看
Isn't that right? And a lot of them are weak in principle, weak in principle.
對不對 那而且他中中間有很多都原則淡書 原則淡書
He thinks about it very carefully
他很精細的去想這件事情
But will you watch it?
可是各位會看嗎
I'm bored. Maybe your first time will look good.
煩了 也許你第一次的話會好好看
After reading the first page, there are still so many pages to read. Forget it.
看了第一頁完之後 還有那麼多頁要看 算了 不管了
agree agree agree
同意 同意 同意
Has anyone disagreed?
有人不同意過嗎
If you don't agree, don't use him
有不同意的話 你就不要去使用他
But the troublesome thing is that we have no way today not to use
但是麻煩的事情就是 我們今天沒有辦法不使用
He has become an indispensable part of our daily life, so many of our services are like this
他變成日常生活中間不可少的 我們太多的服務是這樣子
But everyone, you can take your time to see more and more things
可是各位你可以慢慢看 東西越來越多
Tell us right now that the internal Fins IoT is coming
馬上告訴我們用internel Fins IoT來了
Then today's words, the words of data collection
那今天的話 收集資料的話
He is no longer his collection of data intruding on these things you use
他不再是 他的收集資料侵入到你使用的這些物件
Objects are collecting data anytime, anywhere
物件隨時隨地都在收集資料
The bigger technology behind that
那後面的更大的技術
Everyone heard big data
大家聽到了 big data
Here comes the technology
這個技術來了
technology, the better the technology
技術這個技術要越好
Everyone just needs more information
大家就是越需要更多的資料
Yes or no
是不是
then hear it say
然後再聽到是說
Our new AI for you is here
我們新任你 AI 來了
so we used to
那所以我們以前
We were telling a joke the other day
我們前幾天在講笑話是說
Well, in the future we are actually very convenient
好了 將來我們其實我們很方便
Because we all have AI in front
因為我們都有 AI 在前面
So what if I continue with you?
所以的話呢 我跟你連續的話呢
Actually we were saying
其實我們本來是說
How do you know that what you make is not written by AI
你怎麼知道你弄的東西不是 AI 寫的
Then another sentence says
然後另外一句說
Then how do you know that what I wrote to you was not written by AI
那你怎麼知道我寫給你東西不是 AI 寫的
They communicate with each other than directly
他們比直接在互通了
In fact, we are all doing next to
其實我們都全部都在做的旁邊
In fact, AI is doing everything for us
其實是 AI 在幫我們做的所有事情
In fact, he may be like this in the future
其實未來可能他就是這個樣子
So in this situation
所以在這種情境之下的話
what should we do
我們該怎麼辦
We just talked about the fact
我們剛才談到其實
The thing that should matter is a transparent
應該重要的事情是一個 transparent
Actually we don't need much
其實我們要的不多
one thing you want is
要的一件事情就是
please let us know
請你讓我們大概知道
you are probably currently
你大概現在目前
what technology do you use
你是用什麼樣的技術
What kind of information is being collected from me
在收集我什麼樣的資料
How do you use this information?
這些資料的話你是怎麼用的
what did he do
他造成什麼樣的結果
Today, maybe we can ask the government like this
今天的話也許我們對政府可以這樣要求
But the government did not respond
可是政府也沒有回應
Maybe today, you see, there's no way to respond except the government
今天也許的話 你看 除了政府沒有辦法回應
We also want the government to help us fight some
我們還希望政府來幫助我們來對抗一些
These private, these large corporations
這些私人的 這些大的企業
In fact, if we look from the other side
其實我們在從另外一邊看的話
In fact, some phenomena can also be seen
其實也可以看到一些現象
Facebook Google these two big three
Facebook Google 這兩三大的
This is a so-called mid-level media service industry in the middle of the Internet
這是在網路中間的一個 所謂中階的一個媒介服務業
intermediaries
intermediaries
In fact, their services are almost in the
那他們的服務其實他們其實已經幾乎在
in the middle of our daily life
在我們的日常生活中間了
That's what we can see developing in the U.S.
那可是我們可以看到在美國的發展
Following the development in Europe, the impact on these two companies
跟在歐陸的發展 對這兩個企業的
maybe too same
可能太一樣
Then we have recently seen a series of words in the United States
那我們最近看到一連串的 在美國的話
they will think that
他們會認為是說
because they want to maintain a so-called
因為他們要維持一個所謂的
The technology of this technology
這種科技的technology
or from the Internet
或者從會從講 Internet
Should be a new chart
應該是一個new chart
So these should
所以這些應該
For the intermediary part, he should be neutral
intermediary部分的話 他應該是neutral
So speaking neutral means to say
所以講neutral的話 意思就是說
The government basically does not intervene
政府基本上不會去介入
What about his kind of service?
那這樣子的話呢 他的那種服務啦
he will flourish
他就會蓬勃的發展
Then you can think about it
那你各位可以想想看
What if today's intermediary service industry
如果今天這個中介服務業的話呢
He has a lot of liability
他有非常多的liability
he has many legal responsibilities
他有很多的法律責任
He may worry at every turn
他動輒就可能會擔心
What if I will be sued?
會被告 那告的話怎麼辦
On the other hand, he told you
那另外一方面的話呢 他告訴你說
as long as you don't intervene yourself
只要你不要去自己介入
don't write it yourself
你不要自己去寫
you don't edit
你不要去編輯
you don't check
你不要去檢查
you are all right
你都沒事
this is in america
這是在美國
But what about today?
可是今天的話呢
you can see europe he's not like that
你可以看到歐洲他不是這樣子
So we can see what the EU says
所以我們可以看到歐盟的話呢
he has some cases
他有些案件
Even Canada has some cases
甚至加拿大也有一些案件
for Facebook or for Google
針對Facebook或針對Google
So this is basically thinking
那這個基本上就是在想
what are we looking at
我們在看這個東西幹嘛
we see now
我們現在看是說
these other advanced countries
其他這些先進的國家
how do they come through
他們怎麼樣子來透過
what mechanism to protect these
什麼樣的機制來保護這些
General user or consumer
一般的user或者是消費者
Then we can first see that
那我們先可以看到是
there are some strange
有一些奇異
So how does Taiwan go?
那臺灣到底要怎麼走
Taiwan is a relatively difficult place, we must face the reality
那臺灣又比較難的地方我們必須要面對現實
we are small
我們很小
how much leverage do we have
我們有多大的談判籌碼
If today, I'll go somewhere, I'll deal with one
如果今天的話呢我去處我去處理一個
An intermediaries of transnational
跨國的一個intermediaries
I said you have to conform, if you don’t conform, you can’t do it
我說你必須要符合不符合的話你不能做
will he talk to us
他會理我們嗎
So this is also some reality, so we all know these realities
所以這個也就是一個一些現實所以這些現實我們都知道了
what should we do
那我們該怎麼做
In fact, this is something we should think about
其實這是應該我們要好好去想
There are actually a lot of words today
那今天的話其實有很多的
We just cut this information from the perspective of film and television rights
這些資訊我們剛剛是從影視權的角度切進來
When it comes in, everyone will say that I don’t want to circulate information. I don’t want to circulate information.
切進來的時候大家就會說資訊我不要流通資訊不要流通
not that
不是這意思
The open circulation of information is a very important aspect of the progress of human civilization.
資訊的開放流通是人類文明進步一個非常重要的一個
Base
基礎
you can think about it
大家可以想想看
If there is a free flow of information, our knowledge exchange and our access to information can promote our
資訊的自由流通的話呢我們知識交換我們的資訊的取得可以促進我們的
Knowledge
知識
Let us have a lot of new developments
讓我們有很多的新的發展
It's all a human being exchanging information with each other.
這都是一個人類互相交換資訊所得出來
Say we can't ignore this
說我們也不能夠忽略這件事情
But in the free flow of information
但是在資訊的自由流通
Between the protection of personal privacy
跟個人隱私的保護中間的話
we have to have a balance
我們必須要有一個平衡
If the balance
那這個平衡的話
Today is not about us closing our eyes and covering them
今天不是說我們把眼睛閉起來遮起來的話
If your head is in the sand
頭滿在沙子裡面的話
we don't care
我們什麼都不管
it will naturally become good
它自然就會變成好的
In fact, what we see today is that
今天其實我們看到的情況就是說
Your government must be very real to face such things
你政府必須要很真實的來面對這樣的事情
that information
那資訊的話
you if you say yes
你如果你說好
I should develop Big Data today
我今天應該我要發展Big Data
I want to develop AI
我要發展AI
I want to develop many, many things
我要發展很多很多事情
In fact, I have to provide a lot of information
其實我要必須要提供非常多的資訊
I have to collect a lot of information
我必須要收集非常多的資訊
I want to develop my business industry
我要發展我的生意產業
I also need a lot of information
我也必須要非常多的資訊
we all know that
這我們大家都知道
But on the other hand
但是另外一方面的話
that person's privacy
那個人的隱私
personal information
個人的資料
Shouldn't it also be properly protected?
是不是也應該要得到適當的保護呢
the protection that now provides
那現在提供的保護
Those words are actually what we have to face.
那這些的話其實都是我們必須要去面對的
So I because of time
所以我因為時間關係
The last thing I want to share with you is
最後想跟各位分享的就是
if we personally
如果我們個人
Each of us cares about our personal privacy
我們每個人都很在乎我們個人隱私的話
then you really have to care about privacy
那你真的就要在乎隱私
you have to think about it
你就要去好好想想看
if you do anything today
你今天做了任何一件事情的話
that with your personal privacy
那個跟你個人的隱私
is it related
是不是有關
On the other hand, of course
那當然另外一方面的話
we probably know
我們大概也很清楚
words in the middle of modern society
在現代社會中間的話
many of our services
很多的我們的服務
Or something we want to use in our daily life
或者我們想用的一些日常生活
words of essential things today
今天不可少的東西的話
It is through the exchange of personal data
它是透過交換個人資料
exchanged like this
這樣交換來的
there is no way
這也沒有辦法
On the other hand
那另外一方面的話
We must also use these words of appeal
我們也必須要透過這樣一些呼籲的話
may make everyone understand
可能讓大家理解到說
You can't just sit there and wait
你也不可能只是坐在那邊等
Because if you just sit there and wait
因為如果你只是坐在那邊等的話
If the government does nothing
政府也沒有任何動作的話
Then in this situation
那這個情況之下的話
Many things are only getting worse
很多情形只是越來越糟
And then when you start going in like for example
然後你在開始進去的時候 像譬如說
you can op out
你可以op out
you can refuse
你可以拒絕了
i terminated
我終止了
But here comes the next controversy
可是下面一個爭議就來
What should I do if the front has already flowed out?
那前面已經流出去了怎麼辦
information our most difficult place
資訊我們最困難的地方
Just when the shadow sealed Kang Sheng
就在影封康生的時候
We think the hardest part is
我們是覺得最難的地方就在
Let's assume
我們先假定
i am one i know
我是一個我很清楚
i love my privacy
我愛起我個人的隱私
I also know a lot of things
我也很清楚很多的事情
But the next thing is
但是下一件事情就是
Because the current information
因為現在目前資訊的
the development of a technology
一個科技的發展
we just talked about big data
我們剛剛講到了big data
such a development
這樣的一個發展
It actually becomes a situation
它其實是變成一個情形
is out of our control
是我們沒有辦法控制的
is information
就是資訊
It data its cumulative effect
它資料它的累積的效果
original words
原先的話
You can see the words in the Personal Data Protection Act
你可以看到個人資料保護法裡面的話
it talks a lot
它講了很多
This is also a worldwide
這個也是一個世界性的
Everyone can only talk
大家都只能夠講
If you want to protect a personal data
如果你要保護一個個人資料
Under such circumstances
那這種情況之下的話
there is one thing you can do
有一件事情你可以做
if you do this
做了這件事情的話
Let's just assume it's like this
我們就假設是這個樣子
what's the matter
什麼事情呢
de-identification
就是去識別化
We study the words of many colleagues
我們研究很多同仁的話
What everyone can understand is to say
大家可以理解到的是說
In the personal data protection law
在個人資料保護法裡面的話
referred to in Article 6
第六條裡面提到的
Or in 19, 20
或者在19、20條
It was mentioned on 19 and 80
是19、80那邊提到的
he talked about it
他都談到是說
de-identification
只要是去識別化
He means de-identification
他的意思就是去識別化
This is actually in the EU
這個其實是在歐盟的
He also talks about de-identification
他也是講去識別化
You just have to de-identify
你只要去識別化
Information flow should be no problem
資訊流通應該沒有問題
But he ignored the development of information technology
可是他忽略掉資訊科技的發展
After de-identification, he can re-identify
去識別化之後他可以再識別化
That's the problem now
這就是現在目前的問題
What is it in the words of identification?
在識別化的話是什麼呢
more information
是資訊越多
The easier it is for him to recognize
他再識別越容易
So re-identification
所以re-identification
Originally de-identification
原先是de-identification
Now it's re-identification
現在是re-identification
that on the other hand is
那另外一方面是
we don't know what to say
我們也不知道是說
Even if we really all know about it
即便我們真的都知道這件事情
Everything
每一件事情
If I personally know what went out
我個人知道出去的事情的話
thought about it
都好好想過
But we don't know the information going out
可是我們不知道流出去的資訊
What is the effect of the addition behind him?
他後面的加成的作用是什麼
this is what we don't know
這個就是我們不曉得的
so many things are
所以很多東西是
we do not know
我們不知道
we know
我們知道了
no way to control
也沒有辦法掌控
Under such circumstances
那這種情況之下的話
what should we do
我們怎麼辦
we may ask the government
我們可能請求政府
If the government does nothing
那政府如果都什麼都不做的話
also have problems
也有問題
So I personally would think that
所以我個人會認為是說
In fact, the government should deal with this matter
其實政府應該正對這件事情
then put some
然後把一些
such a difficulty
這樣子的一個困難
He should discuss it openly
他應該要公開的來討論
Therefore, if we pass legislation
所以我們透過立法的方式的話
At least in the middle of the halls of Congress
起碼在國會的殿堂中間的話
he has room for discussion
他是有可以討論的空間
Bundle
把
spread out
攤開來
we make choices
大家做選擇
What about before this?
那在這之前的話呢
can only say
也只能說
Good luck to everyone
各位支求多福
ok thank you guys i'll stop here for now
好謝謝各位我就暫時講到這
this
這個
make this
讓這個
take a breath in your hand
您手上稍微喘一口氣
give him a break
讓他休息一下
this i think we just heard this
這個我想我們剛才聽的這個
Professor Lin has many very enlightening talks
林教授很多很有啟發性的談論
That
那
I find this very interesting
我覺得這個非常有意思
I also think that means
那我也覺得就是說
what he talks about you can see this
他所談的你可以看到這個
How is modern society different from traditional society?
現代社會跟傳統社會多麼的不同
What is he talking about about privacy?
他在講這個隱私權什麼
What do you talk about in traditional society?
你這個交往在傳統社會談的話
must be fun
一定是很有趣的
Because the first we know that this traditional society follows
因為第一個我們知道這個傳統社會跟
between public and private
公私之間的這個
Change
支變
what do you think you can't tell others
你覺得有什麼不可以告訴別人的
should tell others
應該都要告訴別人
you have nothing to hide like this
你沒有什麼可以隱藏的這樣
It can be seen that the changes in this society are indeed very fast.
那可見這個社會的變化的確非常的快
Then I think this is called a study of intellectual history
那我覺得這個叫做一個思想史的研究
very interesting
非常有趣
You can look at traditional people's views on public and private
你可以看傳統人對公跟私的看法
with us modern
跟我們現代人
Because of the changes in social technology
因為這個社會科技的變化
he is very different
他非常的不一樣
So while he was talking I was comparing
所以他一邊在講我就在對照
How would Song-Ming Neo-Confucians respond to him?
這個例如宋明理學家會怎麼回應他
So I think the person who said this wants to talk about this right to privacy
所以覺得說這個要談這個隱私權的人
very problematic
非常有問題
This he becomes you to talk about privacy
這個他變成你要談隱私權
means you must be morally flawed
表示你道德上一定有缺陷
so this is fun
所以這個是很有趣
i just heard
我剛才在聽說
This is what you told Zhu Xi and Wang Yangming in ancient times
這個你到這古代講給朱熙王陽明來講的話
You must be a villain
你這個人一定是個小人
What right do you have to defend your rights?
還有什麼權利要去維護自己的權利
this is even weirder
這個更奇怪
So the society is actually
所以這個社會事實上在
This has changed a lot
這個變化很多了
But now I will leave this time open for you to ask questions
那不過現在我就把這個時間開放給大家提問
Then there is an encouragement among us
那我們中間有一個鼓勵
Anyone who asks a question
凡是有提問者
We'll send a Scientist magazine
我們會送一個科學人雜誌
Only those who have questions
有提問的人才有
This is what I was ordered to announce to you just now
這是我剛才奉命跟大家宣佈的
then we stay
那我們留下
You can see it there in a little while
一點時間就在那裡大家看到了
this is very beautiful
這個非常精美
very good magazine
很好的一個雜誌
then i miss everyone
那我想大家
Will use the industry to feel expensive
會用業的來體貴
Many of the high-tech technologies that the teacher just talked about
老師剛才講的很多科技高科技
The helplessness of using electronic products
使用電子產品的那些無奈
I am
我比較
I don't feel anything
沒有什麼感覺啦
because there is no way
因為這個已經沒有辦法
But you have observed a phenomenon over the past few years
但是各位觀察這幾年來有一個現象
It means you watch any news
就是你們看任何一台新聞
any one
任何一台
news at any time
任何一個時段的新聞
You will see that our news seems to have become one
你都會看到我們的新聞好像都變成了一個
Surveillance Video News
監視錄影器新聞
That
那
In the early years and a few years ago, there was a big debate in the society whether to install a lot of monitors
在早年的再早幾年的時候社會上有很重大的爭論到底要不要設很多的監視器
Of course, the reason of the security unit of the police force is that this is a problem of public security.
那當然警警方的治安單位的理由是說這是治安的問題
Human rights can be compromised a bit, basically I can barely accept it.
那人權可以稍微退讓一點基本上我也勉強可以接受拿來
brought in
拿來在
after playing on tv
電視上播放播放以後
Someone may speak next
接下來可能就有人出來講話
It's almost a mold to operate like this
幾乎是一個模子這樣子去運作這樣子
Some things after sacrificing human rights
犧牲人權以後的一些東西
But if you question this phenomenon today
但是如果你今天去質問這個現象
Then they will also say that we have mosaics
那他們也會說我們有打馬賽克
No, we have to cover our faces too.
不是我們也要把臉遮住
Just like what the teacher said just now
就好像老師剛才講的有去世別化
so-called differentiation
所謂的有去世別化
What does the teacher think about this phenomenon?
老師對這個現象有什麼看法
Thanks
謝謝
In fact, it is useless in the end to say goodbye
其實去世別化倒最後是沒有用的
Because Xiao Min found you out soon
因為蕭敏很快就把你找出來了
Of course, this phenomenon is actually a
那當然這個現象其實是一個
It is also a last resort
也是很不得已
That's called the Great Wall of Electronics
那個叫做電子長城
That many of our governments, local governments or communities
那個我們很多政府地方政府或者是社區
he will feel that we need to restructure
的話他會覺得說我們需要再建構
Our Great Wall of Electronics
我們的電子長城
That's because they figured out that monitors are basically
那因為他們發覺到是說監視器基本上是
A very low cost but
一個很低成本但是的話
The psychological effect is great
心理上的作用是很大的
as long as he is there
他只要在那邊的話
For many others, as we just said, he has a disciplinary function.
其他很多就我們剛才講說他有規訓作用
You don't know if he has it there
他放在那邊你也不知道他是有沒有
Is it useful, you don't know if it is really useful
有沒有用你不知道他是真的有用
On the other hand, I don’t know if anyone
然後另外一方面也不曉得有沒有人當時
I'm really looking at you and I don't know
是真的在看你也不曉得
this is a problem
這是一個問題
Well, what you just said actually involved a few things.
那你剛才講的其實是幾件事情在裡面
One is to say what we see is to say
一個是說我們看到的是說
there are these monitors everywhere
到處有這些監視器
What about these monitors?
那這些監視器的話呢
Everyone knows that now with the facial recognition system
大家知道說現在加上臉部的辨識系統
basically
基本上呢
There is probably nowhere for a man to escape
一個人大概沒有什麼地方可以逃
Wherever you go, everyone will know who you are
你到哪邊大家就知道你是誰
that is fast
那個是很快的
Because the facial recognition system is better now
因為現在那個臉部辨識系統他們更厲害
That day my assistant showed me the new Economics
那天我那個助理他給我看那個新的Economics
He has said that he is not just a facial recognition system
他有講說他不只是臉部辨識系統
He is through technology
他是透過科技
He even backtracked and said
他甚至還倒扣來說
if i knew your genes
如果我知道你基因的話
I also know what you'll look like
我也知道你會長得怎麼樣
Then I heard wow how could this be like this
那我聽說哇這怎麼會是這樣子
it's not that's another thing
這不是那是另外一件事情
But that means there's nothing to hide from
不過這意思就是說無所遁於其行
what about this
那這怎麼辦
There is actually something deeper behind that
那後面其實還有深刻的就是
Can the media do something like this?
媒體可不可以做這樣的事情
of course
那當然
who gave it to the media
那是誰交給媒體
Of course people are our parties
人當然是我們當事人
Like, for example, we used to have a dispute
那像譬如說我們以前常常有一個爭議
it's you
就是那個你透
Let's not talk about the normal one
我們先不談那個一般的那個
you passed through you if we were driving today
你透過了 你如果我們今天是開車
For driving, we have a driving recorder installed.
開車上面的話呢 我們是有裝行車記錄器
What about the driving recorder? When can you use it?
那行車記錄器的話呢 什麼時候你可以行使
Use the record in that driving recorder
使用那個行車記錄器裡面的記錄
The truth is, it should be your own car accident.
道理說 應該是你自己的發生車禍啦
or when there is a flip gain
或者是有翻增益的時候
You can take out the record of your driving recorder
你可以把你的行車記錄器的記錄拿出來
Can you tell someone else what you said in your driving record?
你可不可以把你行車記錄的話 去講別人
to report on someone, to report on someone, to report on someone
去告發別人 去講別人 去檢舉別人
This place actually has problems
這個地方事實上是有問題
Then what I was talking about just now is that behind this
那我剛才在講的是說 這個背後
If we don't talk about the media today, we were talking about it just now.
如果今天還不講媒體 我們剛才在講說
We're doing something else to encourage everyone to report
我們是透過別的方式來鼓勵每個人來檢舉
For some traffic safety accidents, we will report
為了一些交通安全事故的話 我們來檢舉
How about a culture like this?
那這樣子的一個文化的建議好不好
What about everyone we meet in the future?
以後我們碰到每個人的話呢
Is it just
是不是就
In fact, what we need is between people
其實我們需要的是人與人之間
There is also a certain degree of mutual trust
還有某種程度的互信
If the result is slow now
那結果現在慢慢的話
For such a mutual trust, it may take
要把這樣子的一個互信可能都要
have to reach
都要達到
Is that right?
那這樣是不是妥當
I think it's some problem
我是覺得是一些問題
really some problems
真的是一些問題
I know it's a surveillance camera
我知道是監視錄影器
surveillance video recorder
監視錄影器
the back looks like this
後面是這樣子
Surveillance video recorder if it goes down
監視錄影器如果再下去的話
it goes like this
它是這樣談
Surveillance video camera current situation
監視錄影器現在目前情況
before we usually
以前我們通常
if we do anything
我們做任何事情的話
what is usually
通常是什麼事
after what happened to you
等你發生事情之後
We're just starting to hold people accountable
我們才開始來追究責任
let's go find
我們去找
like for example happened bro
像譬如說發生兄弟
For some administrative cases
這個有些行政案件的話
Let's go find the criminal rights suspect
我們再去找到犯罪権疑言
not now
現在目前不是了
now our way words
現在我們的方式的話
already called prevention
已經叫做預防
we're not here to punish after the fact
我們不是在來事後懲罰
but by preventing
而是透過預防
prevention is now
預防就是現在目前
we are actually
我們其實是
imagine
大家想像
data to basically do anything
data基本上要做任何事情
In fact, it provides some preventive
其實就是提供一些預防的
and it's immediate
而且它是立即的
then immediately
然後馬上
and even he can tell you
而且甚至他可以告訴你說
I don't just react immediately
我不只是立即反應
I can prevent you again right away
我是馬上可以再跟你預防
I can tell you
我可以告訴你
What about those places?
那些地方的話呢可能是
may be crime area
可能是犯罪這個區
who speaks for himself
哪個人本身來講的話
he may have some
他可能是有一些
may be guilty
可能在犯的
that or something
那或者是什麼一堆
Then this thing becomes preventive
那這個東西他就變成預防性的
That's what we have now
那這個也就是我們現在目前
maybe some problems
可能一些問題
so what do you want now
所以現在要什麼呢
It's called Video on the Mac
叫做Video on the Mac
so i took it all
所以我全部都收了
Because of current technology
因為現在目前的科技的話
let me have this situation
讓我可以有這種情形
I can put social
我可以把社會上
take everything
所有事情全部收了
through my official
透過我官方的
what else
還有什麼呢
Private Service Efforts
私人的服務的努力
official with what
官方跟什麼
Public and private partnerships
公家跟私人兩個聯手
I put all the information
我就把所有資訊
A person's information has been collected
一個人的資訊全收了
wait till it happens
等到事情發生的時候
I'll look for it again
我再把去找
This was what I was thinking
這個當時在想的事情
is ok
就是OK
ok then you record first
好 那你先錄影吧
words after recording
錄影完之後的話
if you want to use videotape
你要使用錄影帶的話
sorry
對不起
you must have certain
你必須要有一定的
due process
正當程序
you can use this
你才能來使用這個
that now now
那現在目前
do we do something like this
我們有沒有做這樣的事情
This is
這就是
possible concerns
可能關心的問題
when did you my personal information
你什麼時候我個人的什麼資訊
collected by someone out of town
被什麼人出城收集
Then how is he used
然後他怎麼被利用
announced
宣布起來
not very clear
不是很清楚
many people raised their hands
很多人都舉手
It can be seen that the reaction is very enthusiastic
可見這個反應很熱烈
Hello
哈囉
Thank you for your brilliant presentation
謝謝您精闢的演講
just ask a question
就請教一個問題
Two questions should be asked
應該講說兩個問題
The first question is
第一個問題是
Why do people need privacy
為什麼人需要有隱私
there may be a range of answers
可能有一系列的答案
Then ask the vice president about this question at the same time
那這問題同時請教副院長
Physician
學理師的
I studied law with Mr. Lin
跟林老師學法律的
I personally think
那我個人覺得
people need privacy
人需要隱私的
on the first list
在第一個清單上的
The first is to say
第一個就是說
Privacy Helps Creativity
隱私有助於創意
If the individual has no privacy
如果個人沒有隱私的話
society cannot progress
社會不可能進步
no creativity
沒有創意
Then I will ask the two teachers to accept
那接下來就請兩位老師接容
The second question is to say
第二個問題就是說
Living in a situation where all housing and transportation are under surveillance
生活在一個十一住行都在被監控的情況之下
everything is traceable
一切都可回溯
In the past we said that the law is not subject to
以前我們講說法律不受寄往
All can now be mailed to
現在所有都可以受寄往
Essay Questions Sexuality Questions
論文的問題 性平的問題
can be sent to
都可以受寄往
age-leading problem
導人年機的問題
retirement machine problem
退休機的問題
So the whole principle of the law is broken
所以整個法律的原則被破壞了
The whole system logic system is gone
整個系統 邏輯系統不見了
That
那
For insurance, we have to go out for oil and fill in a lot of insurance information
保險的時候我們要出距離油 要填很多保險的資料
ID card phone
身份證 電話
Then when you see a doctor, you have to log in online
然後看病的時候 要上網登錄
And when there is a traffic violation, it will be registered on the Internet.
然後交通違規的時候 網路上都有登記
Traffic Hear me sorry
交通 聽得見 對不起
when traffic violation
交通違規的時候
You can register on the Internet, you know it when you go online
網路上都可以登記得到 你知道上網就知道
When declaring money to a certain political party or religious group
宣宣給某一個政黨或者宗教團體金錢的時候
above all
上面都有
So as soon as these big data comes out, we will already know the result of the next election.
所以這些大數據一出來 下一次選舉的結果 我們就已經知道了
We live in such an era that everyone has the opportunity to be
那生活在這麼一個時代 每個人都有機會成為
protagonist of a news scandal
新聞醜聞的主角
Excuse me
請問
just say when something like this happens
就說當發生這種事情的時候
how to protect yourself
如何保護自己
Is it procedural justice?
是用程序正義嗎
or is there a better way
還是有其他更好的方法
Thanks
謝謝
and facebook recognition
還有就是臉書的辨識
Can you tell if a person is homosexual?
可以知道一個人是不是有同性戀的起象
Especially in the era when Qiyin is developed
尤其是在七陰發達的時代
before birth
還沒有出生的時候
We knew this kid was a genius
我們就知道這個小孩是個天才
there are still handicapped people
還是有殘缺的人
So we live in a time long gone
所以我們生活在一個很久去的時代
full of challenges
充滿了挑戰
Thanks
謝謝
You speak
你講
I speak
我講
I basically don't like living in a society like this
我基本上很不喜歡生活在這樣子的一個社會中間
So I was very concerned about privacy a long time ago
所以我當時對隱私很早以前就是一個很區
district
區
very different requirements
非常區為的一些要求
very very go
非常非常去
A Thousand Cups Request
千杯的要求
I just want to give me a space
我只希望給我一個空間
words in this space
在這個空間裡面的話
I can be close to someone I choose
我可以跟我選擇的親密的人
partner or friend
夥伴或者朋友
we can have very intimate conversations
我們可以很有親密的對話
at least in that space
起碼在那個空間中
In the middle of the space, I'm still alone
空間中間的話 我還是一個人
What about the words in the middle of this space?
那在這個空間中間的話呢
this my friends
這個我的這些朋友們
he knows what i am
他知道我是一個什麼樣子的人
So for some existing
所以對於外面存在的一些
ups and downs they will basically
風風雨雨他們基本上會
that's how it looks
就是這樣看的
so you are at least alone
所以你起碼是一個人
But living in what you just described
可是生活在你剛才描述的
this era
現在這個時代
basically feel very
基本上覺得非常的
special
非常的
very strange
非常奇怪
Then everyone can watch that movie too
那大家也可以看過那個電影
The Truman Show, isn't it?
楚門的世界 是不是
We like to live in the middle of that world
大家喜歡生活在那樣的世界中間
But the future is like that
可是未來就是那個樣子
what shall we do
那我們怎麼辦
actually
其實
I should tell you one thing
應該跟各位講一件事情
Wasn't it one of the things I talked about just now?
剛才不是中間講的一件事情嗎
That is to say, we protect the rights of photographers
就是說我們保障影師權
He actually has a saying
他其實有一種說法
Just afraid of being wronged by others
就是怕被別人錯誤的
understand
理解
twisted by others
被別人扭曲了
Now what you just said about DNA
那現在你剛才講到DNA的
that's been talking about one thing
那一直在講一件事情
Human DNA is read
人DNA被解讀
then what about the enemy
然後敵人怎麼樣
Even after all the enemies are done
敵人即便全部弄完之後
You get another person out again
你再重新弄到一個人出來
Is that the original person of that person?
那個就是那個人的原來的那個人嗎
you know this information
你知道這個資訊
You put together all the information on this person
你把這個人的所有資訊全部匯整起來
is this the person
這就是這個人嗎
Probably not
應該不是吧
Therefore, among our society today
所以我們今天社會中間
kind of missing something
那種缺少什麼東西
In fact, we just talked about each other
其實我們剛才講互相之間
some degree of respect and trust
某種程度的那種尊重信任
is actually important
其實是重要的
When you take these basic things
當你把這些最基本的東西
when everything is knocked out
都打掉的時候
In fact, what has become of human nature
其實人性變成什麼
so that privacy it exists
所以即隱私它存在
It's about humanity
其實是跟人性有關的
Or you say that the earliest start is the instinct of animals
或者你說最早開始是動物的本能
Animals, apart from taking each other's eggs
動物除了是說互相取卵之外
Others basically still have some degree of one
其他基本上都還是有某種程度的一個
on a body it will have a
一個身體上它會有一個
I hope there is still a distance
希望說還是有一個距離
Human basically except for that distance
人的基本上除了那個距離
What you just said is correct
就是你們剛才講的是很對的
Actually some things
其實有些東西的話
very immature
很不成熟的時候
My privacy also protects what I am
我隱私也保障我是什麼
I don't need to carry
我不需要背
That's a bit different from speech
那個跟言論之有點
kinda about where he is the focus
有點關於在這地方他是重點的
i don't need to tell you
我不需要告訴你
i have no reason to tell you
我沒有理由要告訴你
because it's my privacy
因為這是我的隱私
That also protects me a lot
那這也保障了我非常多的事情
give me plenty to think about
可以讓我有充分的可以思考
You said you just talked about human knowledge
你說你剛剛講到人類的知識
Human civilization is actually related to this thing
人類的文明其實跟這東西是有關的
It's important that he has some protection.
他有收到一些保護其實是重要的
but one thing you just mentioned
但你剛剛提到的一件事情
actually took us to another level of discussion
其實把我們提升到另外一層次的討論
what is human nature
就是人性是什麼
What kind of society do we want to pursue?
我們希望追求什麼樣子的一個社會
words in the middle of this society
在這個社會中間的話
how each person is treated
每一個人他是怎麼樣子被看待
Actually we make
其實我們造就
In fact, the reason why this society is like this
其實這個社會之所以是這樣
we made
是我們造就的
because we like a very safe
因為我們喜歡一個非常安全
no society in which danger can occur
沒有任何可能會發生危險的社會
We hope to provide very much
我們希望非常提供到
a service that we use very much
我們非常遍竭的一個服務
what do we want
我們希望什麼
This is what each of us wants
這就是我們每個人不同的希望
and create a society like ours
然後打造出我們這樣的一個社會
So what you need to understand is that
所以各位要理解到的是說
we demand more and more
我們要求越來越多
Because of the development of technology, it is actually beyond our
因為科技的發展它其實是出乎我們
it's beyond our imagination
它是非常我們沒有辦法想像的
growing faster
發展越來越快
but i've always been here
但是我從來就在這邊
Of course, we are doing some technological humanization
當然我們在做也有一些科技人化
I was just thinking about saying that in the middle, we actually need to be more senior.
就在想說中間其實我們必須要前輩一點
What about some things?
對有些事情的話呢
we should think about it
我們應該要多想一想
think about it
多想一想
So like for example we were doing
所以像譬如是說我們當時在做
When the Human General Project
那個Human General Project的時候
When the United States was doing the Human General Project
美國在做Human General Project的時候
then-leader Watson
當時的領導人Watson
The Watson that Norgoi talked about
那個Norgoi講的那個Watson
He basically did one thing by saying
他基本上就做了一件事情就是說
He asked for 3% to 5% of those doing research
他要求把那些做研究的3%到5%
Take it out and do Elsie Ethic
拿出來做Elsie Ethic
Legal and Social Impact
Legal and Social Impact
a study
一個研究
i think he is important
我覺得他是重要的
we are now
我們可是現在目前
Actually, we don't want to talk about this anymore.
其實我們都不要講這個東西了
Let's talk about AI first
我們先講AI就好
AI development
AI的發展
You immediately see the development of AI
你馬上又看到說AI的發展
amazing, isn't it
非常驚人對不對
The AI ​​is also pretty amazing
AI也非常驚人
What if his development continues
如果他的發展下去之後怎麼辦
words at this time
在這個時候的話
This is what we keep saying we can control
這是我們一直在講說我們可以掌控
is that true
是真的嗎
I think this is what we all have in common
我覺得這是我們大家的共同的
common mission
共同的使命
honestly no solution
老實說無解
We give young people a chance to speak
我們讓年輕人有一個發言的機會
Gai, are you starting?
蓋 您是不是起手
good
好
that
那個
Hello President Lin
林總統好
Then what I also want to ask is
然後我也要問的是
Because of the recent EU
就是因為最近歐盟
It should have been last year or the year before the EU
應該要去年還是前年歐盟的時候
through a so-called right of memorandum judgment
通過一個所謂的備忘權的判決
The true meaning of this judgment
那這個判決的真意點
I think the main thing is to say
我覺得主要是在於說
When personal film and television rights and freedom of speech rights
當個人影視權與言論自由權
when a collision occurs
發生衝撞的時候
the court of the European Union
那歐盟的法院
He chose to use his personal film and television rights
他選擇了以個人影視權
there is a more important part
有比較重要的一個部分
so he said
所以他就說
he just said
他就說
He said that with personal film and television rights
他就說了以個人影視權
there is a more important part
有比較重要的一個部分
i want to ask
我想請問一下
that
那個
The professor's or director's view on this matter
教授或所長對於這件事情的看法
right
對
Thanks
謝謝
In fact, there is still a lot of research that can be done.
其實是還可以做很多研究的
But basically it's like this
不過那邊基本上是這樣的
I'll start with a basic response that says
我先做基本的回應就是說
He wants to become concrete and feasible
他要變成具體可行
yes still need to spend
是還要花
He actually has to be a little more detailed
他其實還必須要再更細緻一點
Of course you know the right to be forgotten
那當然也知道說被遺忘權
if the experiment
如果真的實驗的話
What price do we pay for this
我們是用什麼代價來換這個
When the judgment was first
那當時最早判決出來的時候
some people just say
有些人就是說
Well, the history of mankind will
好 那人類的歷史就要
there will be no history
就要沒有歷史了
because everyone can
因為每個人都可以
forgotten
被遺忘
The history of mankind is basically
那人類的歷史基本上都是在
everyone's behavior
每個人行為
He said
他說
this constructed
這個構造出來的
As a result, each piece was removed
結果每個這塊拿掉
Take this piece off this piece
這塊拿掉這塊拿掉
so you can see the right to be forgotten
所以你可以看到被遺忘權
There must be many exceptions behind him
他背後一定有很多例外
he must have many exceptions
他一定有很多例外
including what you just mentioned
包括你剛剛提到說
free speech part
要跟言論自由的部分
he will have an exception
他也會有個例外
but where is that specific thing
但是那個具體東西在哪邊
this stuff needs to be talked about
這東西是需要談的
Then from my legal point of view
那我從法律的人觀點
when you come to see this
來看這件事情的時候
I think there is an American scholar
我覺得有一位美國學者
he speaks very well
他講得非常的好
He said we really need
他說我們真的需要的
not the right to be forgotten
不是被遺忘權
but should be
而是應該是
the right to be forgiven
the right to be forgiven
not forget but forgiven
不是forget 而是forgiven
everyone should know
每個人都應該要知道
you and i can both make mistakes
你我都可能都會犯錯
Everyone should have second chance
每個人都應該有second chance
Will we hold on to this one
我們會不會抱持的這樣子一個
You and I have empathy over there
你我同理心在那邊
Then look at such a thing
然後來看這樣一個事情
that might
那也許會
would maybe
會 也許
we are not sure
我們不確定
But what he said about the right to be forgotten
但是被遺忘權他提出來的話
Behind him is actually everyone else
他背後其實另外大家
you can watch
你可以看
because you can watch another thing
因為你可以再看另外一件事情
is behind some
是背後的一些
political economy issues
政治經濟的問題
This is what the EU ruled
這是歐盟他判的
Canada then
然後加拿大判的
that's american
那是美國的
company
公司
behind him he has many other
他背後他有很多其他的
can be discussed
可以討論
But he is a very important question
不過他是一個非常重要的一個問題
he is a very problem
他是一個非常的問題
Me you wish I had a yes no or something
我 你希望我有一個更說yes no的還是怎麼樣
The gentleman in the back, he goes to the back
那後面那位先生他去後面走
Hello Professor Lin
林教授您好
Well, actually, thank you very much for your wonderful speech just now.
那個其實非常謝謝您剛剛很精彩的演講
right from your speech
就從您演講的過程裡面
You will know that in fact the development of technology
您會知道說其實科技的發展
Including AI, including IoT, including BDIR
包括AI 包括IoT 包括BDIR
These actually come from all over the world
這些其實是普天蓋地而來
Here, if you look at both sides
這邊就如果看兩邊的話
On the one hand, this force of privacy infringement
一邊對隱私權侵害的這個力道
It's like what I just said
等於是就像剛剛也講到說
we wish good luck
我們要自求多福
But that is actually the current technology
可是那個其實現在目前的科技
This is the strength of our Protect Private side
就這一我們Protect Private這邊的力道
Obviously asymmetrical
顯然兩邊不對稱
or this part of our effort
或者說我們去努力的這個部分
Asymmetrical on both sides
兩邊不對稱
Here is actually already
這邊其實是已經是
I don't know what will happen in the future
也不曉得未來會發生什麼事情
invasion of privacy
然後對隱私權的侵害
So sometimes I think a lot
所以有時候想的很多
then more helpless
然後就越無助
Then the more afraid
然後就越恐懼這樣
the one who just mentioned to you
那個向您剛好提到說
There are many of these in our country
像也在我們國家有很多這個
This Ethical or this Effort of Private C
這個Ethical或者是這種Private C的這種Effort
Maybe a few Percent or not even a few Percent
多是幾個Percent 或者甚至沒有幾個Percent
Effort is not big enough so I don't know how to say this two
Effort不夠大 所以我不曉得說這個兩個
Several levels and one level means from the perspective of the country
幾個層次一個層次就是說從國家的角度
In addition, from the perspective of dealing with these large enterprises
另外就從對付這些大企業的角度
And what do we personally want from Sebastian's perspective?
還有我們個人本身要怎麼Sebastian這個角度
Maybe it means that the situation develops like this
可能就是說這個情勢這樣發展
Sometimes the more you understand, the more helpless you will be
有時候就真的是越了解然後就會無助
It's happening so I don't know what we should do
有這種現象 所以我不曉得我們應該怎麼樣
Look at this matter with a more positive attitude
一個比較正面的態度來看這個事情
thanks for this difficult question
謝謝 這個很難的問題
There is another saying that goes like this
另外有一個說法是這樣子
Everyone is a real villain
每個人就是真小人就好了
It means that I have something to hide
意思就是說我不可告人之事
I am like this, but you are also like this
我是這樣子 其實你也是這樣子
The Song and Ming Dynasties just mentioned
剛才講的宋明女學
That is our predecessor Wang Fuyuan
那個是以前我們前任的王復原長
At that time, I asked him about film and television rights.
我那時候有跟他請教過影視權
He told me a few things
他跟我講幾件事
be the first to talk about this
第一個在講這個
He said that the husband of the Song Dynasty
他說宋朝的世代夫
Basically think that there is nothing to hide
基本上會認為無不可告人之事
other than that
那除了這之外的話
He also told me about the May 4th Movement
他也告訴我五四運動的這些
the words of these workers
這些從事的這些工作者的話
Just like Hu's leaders
就像胡氏他們這些領導者
Basically they are exchanging diaries
基本上他們是交換日記
The exchange of diaries is to let you know
交換日記的話是讓你知道
what am i doing what are you doing
我在幹什麼你在幹什麼
Everyone has one like that
大家有形成那樣子的一個
A case of interior
內具的一個情形
Well, on the other hand?
那其實另外一方面的話呢
I found that when he was talking to me about this
我發覺當他在跟我講這件事情的話
I just wanted to say oops
我就想說哎呀
At that time my daughter was in primary school
那時候我女兒他們在讀小學
They also exchange diaries
他們也交換日記
Then you can see today
那你今天可以看到是說
I don't use Facebook yet
我現在還沒有用Facebook
But all my friends around me are using Facebook
可是我周遭朋友全部都在用Facebook
All my friends are on facebook
我朋友全部都在用Facebook
Under such circumstances
那這種情況之下的話
you'll think it's ok
你會覺得是說OK
Is it a change of mind?
是不是觀念變
Because we may the environment in which we grow
因為我們可能我們生長的環境
because we grew up in that
因為我們生長在那種
The era of authoritarian regimes
威權體制那種時代
So for our individual
所以我們對於個人的
personal privacy
個人的一些隱私
is very caring
是非常的在乎
but us
可是我們這些
I'm like Pew my daughter
我像Pew我女兒
words of their generation
他們這一代的話
they live in a happy
他們生活在一個快樂的
Looks like a happy time
看起來是很快樂的一個時代
So basically speaking
所以基本上來講的話呢
like
好像
nothing
沒有什麼嘛
Then on the other hand
然後另外一方面的話
Is it real
是不是真的
Notions of privacy change
隱私的觀念變
I used to think I didn't want to give you
以前我是覺得我不想給你
The current concept has become called Sharing
現在的觀念它變的叫做Sharing
like this one on facebook
就像這個Facebook的這個
the founder
這個創辦者
Zuber was in 2002
朱伯他當時在2002年
Note that it is 2002
注意到是2002年
he just said
他就講是說
actually
其實
I just mentioned that because
我剛剛提到是說因為
Behind Privacy, he is actually related to Social Know
Privacy背後他其實是跟Social Know有關
He said that the current Social Know has changed
他就說其實現在的Social Know已經變了
So what?
所以的話呢
Don't talk to me about Privacy anymore
你們不要再跟我談什麼Privacy了
Because now Social Know has changed
因為現在Social Know變了
so stop talking about this
所以不要再談這個
As a result he was in 2002
結果他在2002年
he was pushing
他那時候在推
That Facebook is pushing a new Privacy Policy
那個Facebook在推新的Privacy Policy
The result is immediately
結果馬上就被
slap in the face
打臉了
Immediately changed again
馬上又改了
But what he said later was actually
可是他後面他講的一句話其實是
is worth saying
是值得我們講的就是說
Is it true that Social norms have changed
是不是真的Social norms變
What we cared about in the past is what we care about now
以前我們在乎的現在目前的話
its new generation it may
它新的generation它可能
it feels nothing
它覺得沒什麼
It feels like nothing needs to be like this
它覺得沒有什麼可以需要這樣子
But in the end, of course, there is a question of
但是最後當然有一個問題就是說
no matter how you look
即便你在怎麼樣子的
can have so many friends
可以有那麼多的朋友
and then there are so many
然後有那麼多的
So much information that can be exchanged with friends
可以跟朋友交換的那麼多的資料
then the last words
然後最後的話
do you keep a little bit
你是不是還保留一點點
I don't want others to know
自己不想給別人知道的
I'm quite curious
這是我蠻好奇的
We also need to pass
也需要我們透過
Maybe big data
可能也是大數據吧
should be through the fact
是應該透過其實
Some empirical research should be done
應該做一些實證的研究
Really do some empirical research
真的要做一些實證研究
what can we dare say
我們才能敢說是什麼
Then what we just talked about are some
那我們剛才講的東西都是一些
Relatively general
比較一般
Everyone seems to think it's something like this
大家好像認為是這個樣子的一種
a concept
一種觀念
So has a concept changed?
所以一個觀念有沒有變
On the other hand, of course
當然另外一方面來講的話
there is another possibility
還有一種可能性
i've been thinking about this
我一直在想這件事情
That means you like, say, Facebook
就是說你像譬如說Facebook
you are so old
你那麼大了
it is already transnational
它已經是跨國的
what else can you do
那你們還能怎麼樣
Of course one thing we want to do is say
當然我們希望做一件事情就是說
We have seen them in order to compete
我們曾經看過他們為了要競爭
So their words they will take this seriously
所以他們的話他們會重視這個
User consumer
User consumer
So find a way to keep the market open to competition
所以想辦法維持市場的開放競爭
Basically, the other side of technology we see is
那科技基本上我們看到的另外一面就是
He is soon to be as big as he is today
他是很快就他今天那麼大
He will be gone tomorrow, right?
他明天就沒有了對不對
he is like this sometimes
他有時候是這樣
But what we're more worried about is where the information goes.
但是我們比較擔心的是那些資訊到哪去了
It's not the problem that you didn't introduce that information.
那些資訊不是你導人的不是那個問題
but that information
而是那個資訊
That information may be like this, he has always existed, right?
那個資訊可能是這樣他一直存在的對不對
That's what we just mentioned
那才是我們剛才提到的是
That question of Right to be, to forget, forgotten
Right to be, to forget, forgotten的那個問題
The words in that place are information
那個地方的話就是資訊
because at any time and forever he always exists
因為隨時永久他一直存在
We hope he doesn't exist, don't act like this
我們希望他不要存在不要這樣子
Then we have to think about it now
那我們現在目前就必須要去想個
very practical question
很實際的問題
What kind of time did these things happen?
到底這些發生了什麼樣子的時害
don't be so scared
你不要那麼恐懼
You don't have to be so fearful
你也不要那麼藉勝恐懼
Then I'll be melancholy over there every day
然後天天在那邊憂鬱
what happened
到底發生什麼事情
That's what we have to know after
那是我們必須要知道之後
we can find a solution
我們才能來找到對策
But the problem is we don't know what's going on right now
但是問題是我們現在也不知道發生什麼事情
that's the trouble
這才是麻煩的事情
So what I said just now is to say
所以我剛才講到就是說
Everyone worked hard to find a way to get him out
大家努力來想辦法讓他出來
Because of this time constraint
因為這個時間上的限制
I want to ask a few people to answer together
我想讓幾位問了一起回答
Then you stay until 12 o'clock in the evening
那你在留到晚上12點
The rest is to discuss with him
剩下要跟他討論
You can go up front and discuss with him
可以到前面跟他討論
Just this one, these three, okay?
就這一位這三位好不好
You all asked together and you answered together
你們都一起問了 你再一起回答
Wait a minute, you can ask the second person and the third person
等一下你第二位 第三位都問得到
Sorry, that teacher just mentioned that
不好意思 那個老師剛剛有提到說那個
This is the age of the Internet of Things
就是這個物聯網時代
Because of the Internet of Things era
因為物聯網時代
we know he collects
我們知道他收集的
The information is quite comprehensive
訊息相當的全面
But look at this in our country
但是觀察我們國家的這個
personal protection law
個人之要保護法
he actually still
他其實還是以
Is it possible to identify individuals
能不能夠識別到個人
Then fine no longer go to authorize the competent authority
然後細不再去授權主管機關
Do some enumerated behaviors to determine whether it is an asset
去做一些列舉的行為來認定是否是個資
But in the era when the teacher just mentioned the Internet of Things
但是在老師剛剛提到物聯網的時代
With the data you collected so comprehensive,
你收集的資料那麼全面的情況下
data set
幾項資料的資料組
Use it to de-identify a person
拿來就可以反識別話一個人
Then I was thinking about this part. I don’t know if I can ask the teacher for advice.
那我是在想說這個部分不知道可不可以跟老師請教
Is there a more suitable way
有沒有一個更適合的一個做法
To confirm what level of information is considered a qualification
來確認怎麼樣的程度的資料算是個資
Or make it a more
或者是說把它做一個更更
It is more in line with a definition like this used in practice
更符合實務上使用的一個這樣子的定義
Ask the teacher this question, thank you
這個問題請教老師謝謝
Hello Professor Lin
林教授你好
I want to go along with the concept of privacy you just said
我想順著你剛才說的隱私觀
Let's talk about this place
這個地方說下去
Because I listened to tonight's lecture and felt
因為我聽了今晚的講座感覺到
Your right to privacy in the context of the current information society
你對現在資訊社會背景下的隱私權
There is a deep worry about being violated
被侵犯有一種深深的隱憂
There is also a pessimistic mood
也有一種悲觀主義的情緒
what about me
那我呢是
Think about it from another perspective
從另外一個面向來想這個問題
because
因為
I think maybe the concept of privacy may indeed undergo some changes under the background of this information
我想也許現在這個資訊背景下隱私觀的確可能會發生一些變化
Then I would like to propose the concepts of absolute privacy, relative privacy and bottom-line privacy
那我想提出絕對隱私相對隱私和底線隱私的概念
because the bottom line is
因為底線也是
because
因為
I think in this context of information
我覺得在這個資訊背景下
we enjoyed the message
我們享受了這個信息
as a resource or a
作為一種資源或者是一種
a convenience of exchange
交換的一種便利
We don't just see a privacy violation
我們不僅僅看到隱私被侵犯的一種
harm to person or personality
對個人或人格的傷害
at the same time
與此同時
have some rights
有一些權利
There are some private rights before the public interest
有一些私的權利在公共利益面前
Is it necessary to release
是不是需要釋放
just for personal sake
就是個人為了
in the public interest or for the benefit of others
公共利益或者為了他人的利益
He may want to release some of his personal space and private information
他可能要釋放一部分自己的私人空間和私人信息
For example, as a public figure or political figure
比如說作為公眾人物或政治人物
we have a right to know about him
我們對他有知情權
In addition, how should the so-called reporting and supervision rights be divided?
另外所謂的檢舉和監督權又怎麼來劃分
Yeah, I thought maybe those powers needed to be protected.
對 我是想這些權力也許都需要保護
It's just that when balancing the various powers
只不過在多種權力之間平衡的時候
When the law is established
法律在制度設立的時候
how to set a rule or boundary
如何設定一個規則或界限
This may be something we need to think about
這可能需要我們思考的問題
you are studying law
您是學法律的
Yes, Thanks
是的 謝謝
and that little girl
還有那位小女生
hello professor
教授您好
what i want to ask is
我想請問的是
just during the speech
就是剛在演講的過程中
You will hear that the development of science and technology
就是會聽到說其實科技的發展
is that they actually depend on some of the privacy that we the people provide
就是他們其實也仰賴我們人民提供的一些隱私權的部分
It feels like our right to privacy has nothing to do with the development of modern technology
那感覺我們的隱私權跟現代科技的發展
is a bit like interdependence
是一個有點像相互依存
Then there is also the concept of interlocking
然後還還相扣的概念
Then what I want to ask is
那我想請問的是
just in technological progress
就是在科技進步
That moment when we still need our privacy
那還需要我們的隱私的這種時刻
It just feels a little bit about our power
就是感覺會有點跟我們的權力
There is a feeling of conflict
又有一點抵觸的感覺
Then what I want to ask is this kind of public welfare part
那我想請問的是在就是這種公益部分
It is a technological advancement
就是要一個科技的進步
with human rights
跟人權部分
between our own privacy
就是我們個人自己的隱私權之間的
That's how to measure the legitimacy
就是那種合法性該怎麼衡量
yes thank you
對 謝謝
I just came back to say
我還是剛剛回到是說
i'm not totally pessimistic
我不是完全悲觀
I just meant to mention
我剛剛的意思只是在提到是說
A free flow of information is very important
資訊的一個自由流通很重要
the free flow of information
那資訊流通的自由流通的話
Of course including his free collection
當然包括他的自由的收集
So I will answer from the back first
所以我先從後面回答
that is
就是說
In this part I just mentioned a suggestion
這部分我剛剛提到了一個建議
in fact it is
事實上就是
make it public for debate
把它公開出來大家來辯論
in the final analysis
就是說到底
what about today
今天的話呢
These data relate to personal data
這些資料涉及到個人資料
Or related to personal film and television materials
或者是涉及到個人影視這些資料
why is it so important
它為什麼那麼的重要
Need to become technology development
需變成是科技發展
or a necessity for its development
或者是某一項它的發展的必要性
let everyone understand
讓大家的理解
If so
那這樣子的話
Maybe we can make a comparison
也許我們有可能可以做一個比較
We all know the situation and do something very understanding
大家都知道情況之下來做一些很了解
Now we don't know
現在目前的話我們也不知道
is a possibly abstract statement
就是一個可能是抽象的說法
Of course we understand that
當然我們理解就是說
the more the merrier
越多越好
how much is that
那要多到什麼程度
to what extent
需要到什麼程度
I just started talking
那當時剛開始講是說
I just need to identify
我只要去識別的話
Then start to get a little bit out of touch with the individual
那就跟個人就開始有點脫離
you use that data
你就去用那個資料
but sometimes
可是有些時候的話
it needs that identifying information
它需要那個識別的資料
So this middle word
所以這個中間的話
Trade-offs are up for debate
取捨之間是需要辯論的
i think it should be
我認為應該是如此
After IoT comes out, basically
那IoT出來之後基本上
In fact, the current difficulty is like this
它其實現在目前困難是這樣子
That is to say, I feel that the Personal Data Protection Act
就是說我覺得個人資料保護法
It has to face a new problem which is to say
它必須要面臨到一個新的問題是說
you thought you meant
你原先認為是說
identify
identify
that thing that is identifiable enough
可足以識別的那個東西
The so-called teaching profile
那個所謂的就教個人資料
Now if we look at it with our current technology
現在如果以我們現在目前科技來看的話
Almost every piece of information is sufficient to identify
幾乎每一筆資料都是足以識別
Insufficient recognition today becomes sufficient recognition tomorrow
今天不足以識別 明天也變成足以識別
So how do you face such a problem?
那怎麼來面對這樣子的一個問題
I think our current personal data protection law
我覺得我們現在目前的個人資料保護法
his words in many places
他在很多地方的話
He hasn't put a question like this
他還沒有把這樣子的一種問題
He brought into his normative thinking
他帶進他的那個規範思維裡面
So I think he's thinking about this part of the question
所以我覺得他在思考這部分的問題的話
It should be like what I just mentioned
也應該就是像我剛才提到的說
should be opened
應該要打開來
Let's discuss and debate
讓大家一起來討論來辯論
What should be like is a reasonable
應該是怎麼樣子才是一個合理的
As I said just now, it is not one-sided
像我剛才講到的說不是一邊倒
he should be a balanced
他應該是一個平衡的
We want to give people a certain degree of space
我們要給人某種程度的一個空間
as mentioned earlier
就像剛才提到的說
may be an underlying
可能是一個底層的
look at the words you use, sorry
你看你用的字眼 對不起
The word you use is the bottom line is the bottom line
你用的字眼是底線是底線的
That's what I don't exchange with you
那個是我不跟你交換的
Other words depend on your personal status
其他的話就看你個人的身份
or comtest
或者comtest
maybe he's somehow
也許他在某程度
is required may be can be collected
是需要可能是可以被收集
can be revealed
可以被揭露的
so it is true
所以也確實
So to resist the contest
所以要抗contest
I think it is to resist the contest
我覺得是要抗contest
That's basically true in Taiwan
那在台灣基本上是確實
some people basically
有些人基本上就
He enjoys less
他就享有比較少一點
some people have more
有些人比較多
But of course this is not the case now
但這個當然現在目前不是這樣子
What we are talking about today is his general
我們今天談的問題是他一般的
He basically wants more information
他基本上是希望多一點的資訊
more information
多一點資訊的話
is better
是比較好一點
Because I'm not an expert on this
因為我不是這方面的專家
so i thought it meant
所以我就覺得是說
need to talk
需要對談
And then this dialogue
然後而且這個對談的話
comparative intellectual circles
不是光是限於比較知識界
probably general public
可能是一般大眾的
let's get to know
一起大家來了解
because we talk a lot about
因為我們很多談到
The final decision is yours
最後的決定是大家
may affect everyone
可能影響到大家
so he needs to be like this
所以他需要是這個樣子
I think I'm not that pessimistic
我是覺得我不是那麼悲觀
i just feel like saying
我只是覺得說
If this kind of development continues
這種發展下去的話
at least we need to know
起碼我們要知道說
This is after I made a choice
這是經過我做過一個選擇的
I made a choice
我做過一個選擇的
if there is no answer
如果都沒有回答的話
Those three come back later
那三位等一下再來
let's go on
我們再繼續講
I think because the time has come
我想因為這個時間到了
Then I think before officially announcing the end
那我想在正式宣布結束之前
I have one more thing to announce
我還有一件事情被交代要宣布
this is the trailer
就是這個預告
this is a teaser
這是一個預告
First on October 17th in October 106
先在106年的10月份的10月17號
Center for Academic Activities at Southport at the Midshore Institute
在中岸研究院的南港的學術活動中心
The first meeting on the second floor of the Zhonghe Research Institute is
中岸研究院的二樓第一會議是
The same feast of knowledge
同樣的一個知識饗宴
We have an Earth Science Institute
我們有一位地球科學研究所的
Researcher Xu Yaru
徐雅如研究員
The lecture will be based on the Great Earthquake of the Last Era
會主講以末代的大地震
take the tsunami
以海嘯
Frequent earthquakes recently
最近常常地震
So you may also be interested in this topic
所以大家也許對這個題目也深感興趣
Well I think we see you today
那我想我們今天看到大家
Interacting with this teacher Lin so enthusiastically
跟這個林老師這麼互動 這麼熱烈
Then said that this speech resonated a lot
然後表示這個演講 引起很多的共鳴
i think wait there may be a little time
我想等一下可能還有一點時間
Let everyone who is intrepid can ask him for advice
讓各位意無畏盡者 可以跟他請教
Then let's applaud now and thank Team Leader Lin
那我們現在就鼓掌謝謝林組長
thank you thank you thank you
謝謝 謝謝 謝謝
thank you all thank you
謝謝大家 謝謝大家